<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-20T14:55:26-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pedro Lopes’s</title><subtitle>My professional website and blog. Come here for news and discussions on physics, scientific management and leadership, and sustainable lifestyle.</subtitle><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><entry><title type="html">Effective team training and who should lead it?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/students_teaching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effective team training and who should lead it?" /><published>2024-10-20T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/students_teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/students_teaching.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lazy blogging. I don’t want to reblog a topic someone else just did. So I will just point people to this interesting piece on <a href="https://condensedconcepts.blogspot.com/2024/06/should-phd-students-choose-to-teach.html">should students teach?</a> at Condensed Concepts. I think the only perspective I should add is that even in private industry, training is extremely important. Onboarding new team members always takes times, does not matter how well-prepared they are. Experience in doing it effectively can be helpful. Understanding the value of it can help save time and money to your organization. Particularly for managers: if you want things done a given way, common recommendation is to train your direct reports on how that is.</p>

<p>Even more importantly, do not forget to tell them “why” you want things that way. It will help people not going out of line, or help you get them back in place when they do. Find more lessons on this in <a href="https://a16z.com/books/the-hard-thing-about-hard-things/">“The Hard Thing About Hard Things”</a> by A16Z.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lazy blogging. I don’t want to reblog a topic someone else just did. So I will just point people to this interesting piece on should students teach? at Condensed Concepts. I think the only perspective I should add is that even in private industry, training is extremely important. Onboarding new team members always takes times, does not matter how well-prepared they are. Experience in doing it effectively can be helpful. Understanding the value of it can help save time and money to your organization. Particularly for managers: if you want things done a given way, common recommendation is to train your direct reports on how that is.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Drive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/14/Drive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drive" /><published>2024-09-14T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-14T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/14/Drive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/14/Drive.html"><![CDATA[<p>In my journey to expand my knowledge from physics to effective management practices, I maintain a steady, yet unhurried reading pace. I find the experience enjoyable—much more engaging than some of my fellow scientists might expect. Many books in this field offer fresh, modern insights, often grounded in solid science. In this post, I’ll give a quick review of a recent favorite: “<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/drive-the-surprising-truth-about-what-motivates-us_daniel-h-pink/246588/?resultid=f8f87171-a9f2-404a-9610-3ab7705fcda7#edition=5980628&amp;idiq=3847557">Drive</a>”, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_H._Pink">Daniel H. Pink</a>.</p>

<p>Amusingly, the author makes my job easy: at the end of the book, he includes “social media” and “cocktail party” summaries. I’ll draw on some of those but also add my own insights.</p>

<p>The book’s main takeaway is that our traditional understanding of motivation—particularly for workers, employees, and even ourselves—is outdated. Not only is this “common wisdom” ineffective for modern needs, but it can also be harmful. What is this outdated wisdom? The author refers to it as the “carrots &amp; sticks” approach: rewarding positive behaviors or achievements and punishing shortcomings.</p>

<p>However, scientific research in psychology, economics, and management suggests a better path. The author argues for a new model of motivation based on three elements:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Autonomy</em> – The desire and ability to direct one’s own life.</li>
  <li><em>Mastery</em> – The drive to improve at something that matters.</li>
  <li><em>Purpose</em> – The sense that what we do is bigger than ourselves and serves others.</li>
</ul>

<p>I find that I can logically relate to many of the arguments put forward by the book supporting the structure above. For example, it suggests that repetitive tasks don’t necessarily have to harm motivation. A basketball player might shoot thousands of hoops to develop <em>mastery</em>, just as I’ve computed an unexciting number of derivatives to get good at calculus. What lies behind this behavior is the idea that humans are capable of intrinsic motivation. While “carrots &amp; sticks” are clear and easy-to-understand extrinsic motivators, they can undermine this intrinsic drive, which is often more powerful, especially for jobs that involve creativity or critical thinking.</p>

<p>D. Pink fills the book with examples showing how these “if-then” extrinsic motivators can harm motivation—crushing creativity, lowering performance, and even discouraging positive behavior. To his credit, the author also acknowledges cases where extrinsic motivation can be beneficial, offering insights into how to align it with the three elements of autonomy, mastery, and purpose. One practical proposition is to shift from “if-then” to “now-that” rewards: offering unexpected rewards only after a task is completed, which can boost motivation without overshadowing intrinsic drive.</p>

<p>Perhaps my favorite idea in the book is that while extrinsic effects don’t usually work for improving motivation, the lack of a reasonable baseline of extrinsic incentives can be highly damaging. As the book points out, things like salaries and benefits need to be taken out of the equation as soon as possible. Workers should receive competitive pay and benefits to create a basic sense of fairness and stability for themselves and their loved ones. Beyond that point, large bonuses or harsh penalties won’t boost productivity or efficiency. That’s when the focus should shift to the three key elements: autonomy, mastery, and purpose. I can definitely see this position mattering in scientific environments.</p>

<p>A key strength of the book is that its arguments aren’t just the author’s opinions—they’re grounded in scientific research by behavioral scientists like (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_L._Deci">Edward Deci</a>) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaly_Csikszentmihalyi">Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi</a>, provided we should appreciate some of these figures may be a bit controversial. I also find that the book’s insights into the role of Purpose in motivation echo themes explored by philosophers, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byung-Chul_Han">Byung-chul Han</a> in his work, “<a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262533379/the-agony-of-eros/">Agony of Eros</a>”.</p>

<p>As with any complex topic, there’s no one-size-fits-all solution to the problem of motivation (particularly in a scientific environment). Still, I find this book thoughtful and full of valuable insights—whether for organizations facing challenges or those looking to elevate their practices.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my journey to expand my knowledge from physics to effective management practices, I maintain a steady, yet unhurried reading pace. I find the experience enjoyable—much more engaging than some of my fellow scientists might expect. Many books in this field offer fresh, modern insights, often grounded in solid science. In this post, I’ll give a quick review of a recent favorite: “Drive”, by Daniel H. Pink.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cash Flower</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/12/cash_flower.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cash Flower" /><published>2024-08-12T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-12T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/08/12/cash_flower</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/12/cash_flower.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I have written posts on the challenges and subtleties of keeping a healthy funding stream for a scientific team. We have also covered some creative practices and opportunities to mitigate some of the risks involved and challenges identified.</p>

<p>This is my own attempt at contributing something to this cause. Keeping track of a group’s finances can be tricky; being able to forecast one’s funding capacity, measuring opportunities against burning rates, can be the difference between being caught unprepared or stably honoring the trust other researchers put on the team manager. Thus, I introduce the “Cash Flower”, a simple Monte Carlo program to provide financial forecasts for an organization funded by typical means a researcher may encounter. Find the source and installation insructions on <a href="https://github.com/pedrolslopes/Cash_Flower">this repo</a>.</p>

<p>Financial data can be input in four different types of categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Stable</strong>: Constant sources of income or expense (e.g., salaries, bills, IP licenses), characterized by monthly average values and variances.</li>
  <li><strong>Singles</strong>: One-time revenue or expense events (e.g., rare large sales, purchases).</li>
  <li><strong>Recurrent</strong>: Repeated cash flows triggered after an initial event (e.g., long-term deals, scholarships, sales or purchase of established products).</li>
  <li><strong>Project</strong>: Milestone-based cash flows tied to project success and timing (e.g. grants).</li>
</ul>

<p>Users may flexibly encode data from their different funding streams in the categories above, with pre-determined probabilities of realizing each event, according to preferences, convenience, or mindset. No single right way of doing it.</p>

<p>Given a set of financial data, Cash Flower outputs some traditional data analytics upon estimating several scenarios of success or failure at achieving revenue or expenses. These analytics include, for the moment, monthly revenue/expense reports, an analysis of the accumulated funding in the organization as function of time, and the risk of going negative. Here goes what the generated plots can look like for some example data:</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/cash_flower_analysis_example.png" title="Cash Flower Data Analysis">
          <img src="/assets/images/cash_flower_analysis_example.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>This program is open source and all are welcome to contribute to the project. Some of my current ideas for improvement include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Better visuals for histogram of monthly expenses and gains.</li>
  <li>Change data gathering and reading scheme so users can take resources from Excel spreadsheets or Pandas dataframes.</li>
  <li>Plot categorized data according to the different types of cashflow events, evaluating how important each is at a given time.</li>
</ul>

<p>Bug reports are also welcome, particularly identifying situations where the program fails!</p>

<p>I hope Cash Flower will help scientific managers and individual contributors alike to better monitor the financial health of their endeavours!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: as of the writing of this post, these resources have not yet been tested on realistic scenarios.</em></p>

<p><em>For this one I owe a big thanks to my wife, Marianne, for the support, helping with debugging, and feature suggestions. Hope this will be useful to her one day! I also owe the idea for creating this program to Yuval Boger, “The Superposition Guy”.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently I have written posts on the challenges and subtleties of keeping a healthy funding stream for a scientific team. We have also covered some creative practices and opportunities to mitigate some of the risks involved and challenges identified.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on stable science funding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/14/stable_funding.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on stable science funding" /><published>2024-07-14T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-07-14T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/07/14/stable_funding</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/07/14/stable_funding.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a research manager, securing stable funding for your group is a critical responsibility. Your team, whether students or professionals, relies on you as the scientific leader to provide a stable environment for creation, skill development, and professional growth. Breaching that trust can be a significant setback.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-01570-y?utm_source=Live+Audience&amp;utm_campaign=29096efd03-nature-briefing-daily-20240529&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_b27a691814-29096efd03-52510728">recent article</a> caught my attention on the topic of “what to do when funding runs dry.” Funding for science can be intermittent if your organization lacks a mechanism for continuous stream support. It often falls on the scientific leader or manager to constantly negotiate or sell the importance of their work. If they actively participate in research and the funding landscape is unpredictable, conflicting priorities – as many scientists dislike the “selling” aspect of the job – may lead to overlooking impending financial threats to the team.</p>

<p>The article presents several suggestions on how to deal with this reality, some of which I was unaware were possible. In this post, I will focus on those suggestions rather than the statistics on funding difficulties in certain countries. I will expand on ideas mentioned in the article, as well as bring my own suggestions based on my experience and learning from my professional network.</p>

<h3 id="the-spts-9-thoughts-on-how-to-deal-with-intermittent-funding">The SPTS 9 thoughts on how to deal with intermittent funding:</h3>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Communicate with Program Officers</strong>: If your funding sources are usually governmental grants, talk to your program officers in case of trouble. While they may be demanding on proposal acceptance, their goal is likely the success of science and education. They are there to help you. Challenges in getting funded are not personal.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Know your program officers</strong>: while on that point, note that knowing your program officers and vice versa can really help you in understanding their priorities, and them understand details your interests and provide you feedback. So, find opportunities to meet them, for example as mentioned in <a href="https://pedrolslopes.github.io/2024/02/25/Policy_sabbatical.html">my post</a> on sabbaticals in government.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Utilize Bridge Grants</strong>: Some institutions offer “bridge grants” – emergency mechanisms to help researchers connect different funding periods in case of trouble, particularly when pivoting to new research directions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Engage with Your Employer</strong>: And on the same flavor as above, your employer (university or otherwise) is not your enemy either. Talk to them – they may have mechanisms in place to help you connect between grants or customer projects.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>And vice-versa</strong>: Maybe the above is also a tip for employers to think about setting up such mechanisms in place! The “group rejuvenation sabbatical” mentioned in he article sounds like an innovative idea!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Diversify Funding Sources</strong>: Hedge your odds by applying to multiple sources of support (different funding agencies, industry relations, or philanthropy (see also my previous post on <a href="https://pedrolslopes.github.io/2024/03/31/Philantropy.html">the latter</a>)). However, be cautious not to let writing too many applications overwhelm you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Plan Ahead</strong>: The article mentions the importance of “Planning Ahead”, and includes some interesting tips on no-cost extensions to spend unused funds. Proper planning helps predict trouble. Run adequate budget analyses for your lab, including your cash runway. Stay tuned for a tool I’m developing to assist with this!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Invest in Supply-Chain Autonomy</strong>: Experimentalists tend to struggle more with funding than theorists. Consider investing in your supply-chain autonomy by machining your own parts. While it won’t solve a funding gap, it will be more cost-effective, mitigate risks, boost team confidence, and perhaps lead to entrepreneurial opportunities. Tapping in the open-sourcing community and modern computer-aided design and manufacture can really provide students with meaningful skills for future work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Collaborate and Share Resources</strong>: Team up with other researchers and share resources. Teams may have better odds of getting larger, longer-lasting funds as part of a program. If your curiosity aligns with a funding agency’s mission, mission-oriented programs can also represent good opportunities.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Funding science and research will always be challenging, but it is undeniably important work. If mechanisms for stable funding did not exist, research universities would not function as institutions. Engaging with the system is crucial for any maturing scientific leader.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a research manager, securing stable funding for your group is a critical responsibility. Your team, whether students or professionals, relies on you as the scientific leader to provide a stable environment for creation, skill development, and professional growth. Breaching that trust can be a significant setback.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Words of Wisdom #1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/17/WoW_Shengtao.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Words of Wisdom #1" /><published>2024-06-17T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/17/WoW_Shengtao</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/17/WoW_Shengtao.html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a new blog series at Set Physics to Stun! While most of my posts are based on my own experience, observations, or creations in science and scientific management, I wanted to bring in some opinions beyond my biases. So hereby I start “Words of Wisdom”, a blogging series where I shortly interview seasoned professionals in the world of science management. I will tap their expertise and bring you their inspiring words to burning questions.</p>

<p>For this first entry, I bring words from my own work colleague Shengtao Wang. Shengtao is a quantum information scientist with a career spanning Singapore, Michigan, and most recently Harvard University in Boston. He is one of QuEra Computing’s first employees and manages a 10+ team of theorists and computer scientists working in algorithms and applications.</p>

<p>Here we go for Shengtao’s words of wisdom:</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> When it comes to time allocation, what would you say are the main challenges and peculiarities of managing a scientific team?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SW:</em> In a fast-paced environment where priorities are fluid, aligning a team’s priorities and motivations becomes crucial. If you manage to do this effectively, even when delays occur in some projects, you will know that the team’s strong motivation is focused on the highest priorities.</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> How do you view motivation? What are the key factors that keep a scientific team motivated?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SW:</em> To stay motivated, scientists truly need room for creativity and critical thinking. Discovery holds cultural importance for scientists. I believe it’s crucial for team managers and leaders to secure and respect this space for creativity.</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> What is the main “danger” or “tripping hazard” a scientific manager may face?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SW:</em> When a scientific leader lacks a strong vision and a clear direction, the team risks becoming mediocre, and their output may be less impactful. On the other hand, team managers and leaders should avoid micromanaging how goals and visions are achieved. Instead, they should allow highly motivated individuals to find their own paths to success.</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> How do you distinguish the above in an academic vs private environments?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SW:</em> In my view, the industry setting requires considerably more management due to many more competing factors and priorities. Academic labs can thrive on self-organization and adapt naturally to changing research directions. In contrast, in industry settings, it is crucial for individual and team goals to align with the company’s vision and objectives. Consequently, more management and coordination both within and between teams are essential for overall success.</p>

<p>That is it! Thanks Shengtao for your Words of Wisdom! Set Physics to Stun hears you!</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starting a new blog series at Set Physics to Stun! While most of my posts are based on my own experience, observations, or creations in science and scientific management, I wanted to bring in some opinions beyond my biases. So hereby I start “Words of Wisdom”, a blogging series where I shortly interview seasoned professionals in the world of science management. I will tap their expertise and bring you their inspiring words to burning questions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assessing PhD Assessments</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/21/PhD_assessment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assessing PhD Assessments" /><published>2024-04-21T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-21T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/21/PhD_assessment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/21/PhD_assessment.html"><![CDATA[<p>A (total!) eclipse, travel, and hackathons have slowed down my blogging. That together with, for the first time, being asked to do the technical review of a book for a friend. All relevant experience and service, if anyone ask me! But I am ready to come back to Setting Physics to Stun!</p>

<p>This time I want to visit the topic of how adequate PhD assessment is. This topic is a little more academic than general scientific management, but I had some interactions with friends on the topic which it got me thinking. Also, in my (quantum) industry, I am frequently questioned by junior students on whether they should pursue a PhD to seek a scientific career in the field. So maybe this is a good chance to address these questions a bit.</p>

<p>The topic was brought to me by reading a Nature Editorial <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00718-0?utm_source=Live+Audience&amp;utm_campaign=adeec3770a-briefing-dy-20240313&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_b27a691814-adeec3770a-52510728">“Bring the PhD assessment to the twenty-first century”</a> which was followed up by a poll. When I brought this up to colleagues that work in academia, I feel like they did not fully appreciate the issue being raised. Their claim was that “the market - both academic and private - seems to be happy with the process” given that rarely a person with a PhD - in physics, at least - find themselves unemployed. Fair statement. The editorial article itself highlights that not all PhD training is stuck in the past. But it strikes me as true that innovation and discovery in the field of education is struggling to find its way into the doctorate process (and generally in higher education at research institutions, given that successful postdocs and grad students - again, at least in physics - tend to be discouraged from engaging with teaching research too deeply).</p>

<p>To try and ground this conversation, and hopefully help junior students understand what the commitment to do a PhD entails, let’s at least try to formalize a definition of the purpose of a PhD program:</p>

<p class="notice--warning">The <a href="https://www.qaa.ac.uk/docs/qaa/guidance/guidance-rdap-academic-staff-mar-2014.pdf?sfvrsn=356f781_6">British Quality Assurance Agency for Higher Education</a> states that a doctorate student should demonstrate the creation and interpretation of new knowledge that extends the forefront of the discipline and merits publication.</p>

<p>This definition may vary slightly from place to place, but makes it clear why a PhD experience can be relevant in industries of promising but not yet mature technologies (quantum tech, gene therapy, arguably AI before 2023):  the path to commercialization and productization of the tech requires it to finish evolving, often requiring multiple knowledge breakthroughs at the forefront – what a PhD trains for.</p>

<p>The editorial cites a couple of relevant references, <a href="https://ora.ox.ac.uk/objects/uuid:07291f0e-e80b-4b06-a6af-b3ac8b90a00e">a looong thesis</a> and a <a href="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/09684880310471506/full/html">short-but-not-so-recent article</a>. I confess the thesis was too much of a commitment for me to study, but the article may help us itemize some concrete examples about what parts of the PhD assessment process do not have uniform clarity throughout the community:</p>

<ul>
  <li>How to determine a PhD committee? Should the student have a say? Should it be formed by experts only?</li>
  <li>What matters most: the thesis write-up or the defense oral presentation? (Both are typically required. Neither is typically sufficient)</li>
  <li>What is the purpose of the oral presentation? What should be its length? Is it just a rite of passage? Should it be private or public?</li>
</ul>

<p>The list goes on.</p>

<p>Again, many, if not most, of these questions are decidedly addressed in the regulations and administrative rules of specific programs at different universities. So, for new students, perhaps these bring you some suggestions of questions to ask once you get accepted in a program. The broader questions are: (i) why there is no more common agreement across different institutions about how these should be organized? And (ii) how different choices for the above impact the experience and learning of the students?</p>

<p>I hope this brings up some relevant perspectives on scientific management on what says respect to the scientists themselves, and helps them analyze the culture of the organizations they decide to join.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A (total!) eclipse, travel, and hackathons have slowed down my blogging. That together with, for the first time, being asked to do the technical review of a book for a friend. All relevant experience and service, if anyone ask me! But I am ready to come back to Setting Physics to Stun!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Philanthropy in the Landscape of Science Funding</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/31/Philantropy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Philanthropy in the Landscape of Science Funding" /><published>2024-03-31T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-03-31T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/31/Philantropy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/31/Philantropy.html"><![CDATA[<p>A busy week of teaching and preparing for an upcoming trip to Quebec to witness the eclipse left little time for blogging. Nonetheless, I’ve been mulling over some discussion-worthy topics!</p>

<p>The different funding mechanisms for science, both in academia and elsewhere, have been on my mind lately. This reminded me of two insightful articles from late 2022 and early 2023 – one in <a href="https://pubs.aip.org/physicstoday/article/75/11/24/2848605/Philanthropy-plays-a-growing-role-in-funding-US">Physics Today</a> and another in the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-00077-2">Careers Feature section of Nature</a>. These articles delve into the role of philanthropy in supporting research (which I guess naturally plays a more significant part in science backed by academia or non-profit organizations, rather than in private institutions). The topic also resonates with the recent news of the super-wealthy’s request at Davos, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/jan/17/wealth-tax-super-rich-davos-abigail-disney-brian-cox-valerie-rockefeller#:~:text=%E2%80%9COur%20request%20is%20simple%3A%20we,harm%20our%20nations'%20economic%20growth.">asking to be more properly taxed</a>. It seems plausible to me that this request stems from a situation where inequality grew so big that some wealthy individuals are struggling to even donate impactfully. But I digress.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://pubs.aip.org/physicstoday/article/75/11/24/2848605/Philanthropy-plays-a-growing-role-in-funding-US">first article</a> from Physics Today analyzes the growing influence of private donors on the physical sciences and contrasts this source with other traditional ways to fund science, namely federal grants. The article features an intriguing figure, which, with a bit of digging, can be traced back to the strategic planning of the <a href="https://sciencephilanthropyalliance.org/#">Science Philanthropy Alliance</a> organization. Since the document is public, I’ve reproduced the corresponding figure here:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/sciencephilalliance.png" alt="image-center" class="align-center" style="width: 70%;" /></p>

<p>The red curve represents sources of philanthropic origin via non-profit foundations and donations to higher education institutions (and their endowment funds). The contribution from philanthropic sources may be even higher, as this data excludes individual donors.</p>

<p>As the article suggests, this plot tells a story: historically, contributions from wealthy individuals to science were of central importance. In the US, names like Rockefeller and Carnegie are associated with several institutions of higher education. The Cold War years witnessed a sharp increase in government support for science, and private funders shifted their efforts elsewhere. However, public support for science has been decreasing proportionally, and philanthropic sources have correspondingly risen as donors turn their attention back to helping researchers as a way to give back to society.</p>

<p>Private donations can positively influence science in many ways. The process of spending resources can be less bureaucratic and more flexible. It can more easily allow pivoting research directions – something challenging to do mid-grant when specific deliverables are requested during project planning – and can provide a pathway for scientists to transition to new areas of focus. This reconversion is typically difficult to achieve, as public funds tend to require a prior reputation in a field for researchers to successfully obtain funding. The article also mentions how the flexibility of philanthropic funding can foster more risk-taking in science, a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00929-5?utm_source=Live+Audience&amp;utm_campaign=45bbc57f69-briefing-dy-20240326&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_b27a691814-45bbc57f69-52510728">subject of intense discussion</a>. Finally, private funds can complement other sources; for example, some sources can address only capital or infrastructure expenditures, while private funds tend to cover personnel and operations – a perfect match!</p>

<p>However, not everything is perfect and easy. The article gathers advice for caution from scientists previously successful at garnering donor funding. These include being mindful of</p>
<ul>
  <li>money that is too restrictive,</li>
  <li>donors who expect too much recognition,</li>
  <li>and donors who feel they have the right to call the shots (like on hiring decisions).</li>
</ul>

<p>Another issue I see: as the article mentions, securing philanthropic funds requires a good dose of personal touch and relationships. Access to the right communities and the type of engagement and relationships developed depend heavily on opportunities and culture. This may pose a barrier for individuals from minority groups and affect diversity, equity, and inclusion outcomes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-00077-2">The second article</a> provides different resources and information on the topic. It takes the position of interviewing scientists who successfully obtained donations for their research and shares their stories. The result is a good collection of advice on navigating the process. On a personal note, one of the interviewees tells some inspiring stories from his position as a researcher in Brazil and how different philanthropic organizations such as the <a href="https://serrapilheira.org/en/">Instituto Serra Pilheira</a> – apparently the only foundation to support science with private donations in Brazil – helped him remain engaged with the global scientific community. If you’ve read my other blog entries, you’ll remember me mentioning the issues surrounding the Brazilian scientific diaspora caused by, among other reasons, the insecurity of funding for science in Brazil.</p>

<p>In summary, both articles agree: some hedging is advised. Researchers should try to view the ecosystem of funding alternatives holistically and not bet on a single direction, not overlooking traditional federal grants, but remembering that significant alternatives exist.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A busy week of teaching and preparing for an upcoming trip to Quebec to witness the eclipse left little time for blogging. Nonetheless, I’ve been mulling over some discussion-worthy topics!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Showcasing Emergence in Scientific Collaborations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/16/Pub_network.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Showcasing Emergence in Scientific Collaborations" /><published>2024-03-16T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-03-16T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/16/Pub_network</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/16/Pub_network.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post tells a bit of my own professional story as I left life as a pure researcher, and then moves toward introducing my first managerial tool for scientific collaborations. Hope you enjoy it!</em></p>

<p>It was early 2020, before the surprising upheaval of life caused by Covid-19. I had found my first non-research job: to manage and pave the way for the success of the <a href="https://qmi.ubc.ca/">Stewart Blusson Quantum Matter Institute Grand Challenges</a> research program. This program aimed to foster coherence in research among the institute’s members, prioritizing and focusing research topics for greater impact and value for the community.</p>

<p>The origin of this Grand Challenges program can be traced back to discussions among the Institute’s scientific advisory board. Simplifying a complex story, these advisers questioned why significant funds should be injected into a thematic institute if it merely resulted in already established research groups continuing to work independently. Essentially, there was a view that merely uniting independent researchers under a well-funded endeavor wasn’t enough to drive transformative change and leadership. To make the institute an undisputed global leader in its field. Many of its groups were already adequately funded, so achieving such scientific leadership was seen to require a coherent, laser-focused approach on the most impactful work possible.</p>

<p>Echoing Phil Anderson’s timeless <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.177.4047.393">“more is different”</a>, widely influential across the quantum matter community, the sentiment was that to achieve scientific prominence and success, the “institute must be more than the sum of its parts.” Primary Investigators were brought together, themes were selected, and charters of work and project proposals began to take shape. I was brought in to oversee the management of the program.</p>

<p>Program and project management in the physics community are not extensively documented, and tools and methodologies are not well developed. This is partly because deliverables tend to be uncertain, making it tricky to track progress and evaluate performance using formal approaches. When I began working on the Grand Challenges, I underwent professional training in project management. However, many concepts were not directly transferable. Moreover, attempting to impose standards developed by outsider communities on academic groups with different pressures and goals was likely to backfire and generate conflict. Nevertheless, I was enthusiastic about the opportunity to innovate how research could be conducted and managed.</p>

<p>As upper management pressured the Grand Challenges team to create deliverables and performance indicators, I decided to revisit the program’s origin. The success of the work should indicate that the program was fostering coherence within the institute, ensuring it was more than the sum of its individual parts. Being a mathy guy and having a career centered around correlated matter, I embraced ambition. I conceived an academic social network for the Grand Challenges Principal Investigators. This tool, I believed, would be visually impactful for reporting - facilitating communication with donors and advisory boards - and enable precise course corrections and policy changes to achieve success. Moreover, its geeky appeal made it likely to be embraced by academics without resistance to managerial practices, which was a personal favorite aspect.</p>

<p>So what did this look like? Here goes an example:</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/network_plot.png" title="pub network">
          <img src="/assets/images/network_plot.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>I assigned professors in a given project academic names (Professor A, B, etc., in this example) and represented them as nodes in a graph (the blue disks). With the help of a colleague, I obtained a database containing all the papers of the institute’s members. I then wrote a script to filter this database, creating a list of pairs of names whenever two professors co-authored a scientific publication. These pairs were represented as red edges on the graph, symbolizing collaboration—instances where individual members joined efforts to address a single problem. To depict the strength of collaboration, the thickness of the red connections was made proportional to the number of papers two researchers co-authored. The more papers they shared, the stronger their collaboration!</p>

<p>Now how could I create a sense of “where this program is going”? I decided to examine sub-projects proposed in the program. As these involved multiple groups, I created a list of “collaborations in development.” If an edge didn’t exist between two professors but collaboration was underway, I depicted it as a dashed line. The web of dashed lines indicated the program’s capacity to foster a more robust collaborative network, paving a path to make the institute “more than the sum of its parts.” For reporting and tracking, once a publication came together, boom! The list of publications could be updated, the dashed line would become red, and one could visualize the change in the network directly.</p>

<p>Of course, these are all qualitative ways of looking at the problem. But again, graph theory is a well-established branch of mathematics. There are several quantities one can use to obtain quantitative information on the state of one such network. Here go a few I like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Degree Distribution: the distribution of degrees (number of connections) can provide insights into the connectivity of the network. In our academic network, we would be looking at the number of collaborations each professor has.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Centrality Measures: Centrality measures identify the most important nodes in the network. Some measures of centrality include:
    <ul>
      <li>Degree Centrality: the number of connections each node has.</li>
      <li>Betweenness Centrality: the number of shortest paths that pass through a node. This indicates the node’s importance as a bridge between different parts of the network.</li>
      <li>Closeness Centrality: this measures how close a node is to all other nodes in the network, indicating its ability to quickly  spread information.</li>
      <li>Clustering Coefficient: the degree to which nodes tend to cluster together. In our research network, this indicates the presence of tightly-knit research sub-groups.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Path Length Distribution: the distribution of shortest path lengths between nodes, which provides insights into the overall structure and connectivity of the network.</li>
</ul>

<p>Reports with these data could then be generated for analysis. I habitually provided reports on the “current state” of the network (i.e., without the dashed lines), and “target state” (including the dashed lines) for comparison. These can be plotted in bar charts and set up thes side-by-side for analysis. For example, for the mock data of the graph above, we would have</p>

<figure class="half ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/Academic%20Network%20Current%20State.png" title="report current">
          <img src="/assets/images/Academic%20Network%20Current%20State.png" alt="report current" />
      </a>
    
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/Academic%20Network%20Target%20State.png" title="report target">
          <img src="/assets/images/Academic%20Network%20Target%20State.png" alt="report target" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>Though there’s room for improvement—for example, plotting both on the same axes for easier comparison—the tool proved effective. It not only structured early program reporting but also aided researchers in grant applications, helping secure nearly seven-figure funding. While the solidity of research programs was the main driver of such success, I am happy I could play a small part in this achievement.</p>

<p>Managerial teams are not always equipped to program tools like this, nor to determine suitable graph-based metrics. I’ve heard that reproducing what I initiated with these networks became challenging after my departure from the Stewart Blusson Quantum Matter Institute. Recently, with renewed energy, I revisited my code and polished it to make it easier to reuse and share. If you are interested in trying it, you can find what I hope is a straightforward codebase on <a href="https://www.github.com/pedrolslopes/publishing_network">this Github repo</a>. Once you’ve successfully generated your data, running</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>python research_network_analyzer.py
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>will generate figures of your network, plots with data analysis, and text files with numerical report data for both the current and target states of your network. As mentioned above, there is space for improvement, but I hope this can now be useful to more people!</p>

<p>And with that, the story—or perhaps this chapter—ends. The Grand Challenges program is ongoing, and research there continues to thrive. Many former researchers who participated in the program have moved on to prominent positions in academia and industry. Likewise, my journey to improve managerial practices in research environments continues to evolve.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post tells a bit of my own professional story as I left life as a pure researcher, and then moves toward introducing my first managerial tool for scientific collaborations. Hope you enjoy it!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Policy sabbaticals, a bit of Dworkin, a bit of Dweck</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/25/Policy_sabbatical.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policy sabbaticals, a bit of Dworkin, a bit of Dweck" /><published>2024-02-25T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/25/Policy_sabbatical</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/25/Policy_sabbatical.html"><![CDATA[<p>As I keep trying to create technical content, columns on Nature continue to interrupt me. Seems like these really are good sources of inspiration.</p>

<p>This time the topic is “what to do in a sabbatical year”?</p>

<p class="notice--warning">Traditionally, tenured university professors receive support - partial or total - to spend periods of time working outside of their home institutions. These sabbatical periods are usually taken once every 7 years (for sabbaticals lasting 12 months) or every 3.5 years (for 6 months). The goal of this is to propitiate researchers with opportunities to engage with new communities, research topics, and stimulate relations between institutions.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00479-w">World View</a> column last week, Jordan Dworkin provides an uncommon suggestion: spend time in government. I won’t be repetitive and reproduce all comments and reasoning made in the article: they are very sound and meaningful. I strongly recommend my colleagues who work at universities and research institutes to read this article and look kindly at the points made.</p>

<p>I do, however, have a feeling that many of my friends in the physical sciences might believe that the impact they can make in policy matters less than that of health and social scientists. So, let me provide a clear example of the type of frustration this kind of attitude can bring back to the community.</p>

<p>This past week, one of my academic friends sent me a message containing the following screenshot from a conversation in the X platform:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Galitski_quantum_hype.jpeg" alt="image-center" class="align-center" style="width: 45%;" /></p>

<p>In quantum computing, the complaint of hype and misdirected resource allocation is a constant topic. The importance of government in funding sustained research and development, but also in helping fund the commercialization of quantum technologies, cannot be overstated. Nor should be its role in fostering the relations between researchers and private industry, which indeed are very healthy. Creating career opportunities for youth among the physical sciences is one of my favorite aspects of the quantum tech industry. But this stereotypical attitude of academics seeing politicians as incapable of having meaningful conversations on topics with technical depth, does not help.</p>

<p>I’d like to take a position more aligned with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindset#Fixed_and_growth_mindsets">growth mindset</a> and say there is no “catch-22”. No conversation I have ever had with politically engaged folks suggests that. With enough time and attention, and the right environment, I think it is very possible to help inform policy-makers on physical sciences and quantum technologies. Following Jordan Dworkin’s proposition and promoting more Tours of Service among the physics community seems a good starting idea for that.</p>

<p>And without trying to open a can of worms, I don’t want to miss the opportunity here: the vast majority of the members of the quantum tech community I know are seriously engaged in distributing sound information, opinions, and recommendations. I would not deny having seen hype, but I don’t see it being systematic or, so far, damaging. As far as business goes, commercialization of quantum tech is not an easy subject and the whole industry is working to find the sustainable paths to success.</p>

<p><em>And to be sure: these opinions are all personal and should never be assumed to be supported by my employer.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As I keep trying to create technical content, columns on Nature continue to interrupt me. Seems like these really are good sources of inspiration.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientifically Speaking: Trust, Policy, and a Dash of Pre-Prints</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/18/Science_comms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientifically Speaking: Trust, Policy, and a Dash of Pre-Prints" /><published>2024-02-18T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-18T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/18/Science_comms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/18/Science_comms.html"><![CDATA[<p>While I was working on a much more technical first post, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00420-1">Nature released a News article</a> on a core raison-d’être of this blog: the trust of public in scientists, scientist engagement with policy making, and their involvement with society. So, let’s take this opportunity to delve into this topic.</p>

<p>The Nature News was prompted by <a href="https://osf.io/preprints/osf/6ay7s">a new pre-printed article</a> where researchers led by Viktoria Cologna (University of Zürich) conducted extended interviews and data analysis on the “Trust in scientists and their role in society across 67 countries”.</p>

<p class="notice--warning">For those unfamiliar with pre-prints, these are scientific articles distributed openly before peer-review, the process usually required for formal scientific validation. Despite lacking validation by the scientific community, pre-prints facilitate access to research for anyone interested, thereby lowering barriers to scientific development globally and fostering transparent communication with non-experts (as articles would otherwise be behind paywalls). Several servers for pre-prints exist; the most famous among the physical sciences community is known as the <a href="https://arxiv.org/">arXiv</a>. I hear biologists tend to use the <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/">bioRxiv<a></a>.</a></p>

<p>Let’s look at some key points of the work:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Good news! The study found no widespread lack of trust in scientists by the public on a global scale.</li>
  <li>However, significant local variations were observed both between and within countries, with cultural differences impacting trust and correlations with political tendencies.</li>
  <li>The study revealed that scientists are perceived as not being very open to feedback, with over 80% of the public expressing a desire for more communication from scientists.</li>
  <li>While no country studied had an overall lack of trust in science, the authors caution against disregarding the impact of even small minorities’ mistrust, which can have significant repercussions.</li>
  <li>Societies seem to want scientists to prioritize health and energy as research topics, but believe current focus on those topics is insufficient. Opinion is that too much emphasis is given to matters of defense and military applications.</li>
</ol>

<p>Points 3-5 catch my attention. So let me explore them further.</p>

<p>On point 3, the authors promote a list of recommendations including: promoting more transparent practices regarding funding and data sources, and investing more in public communications. Since scientists are seen as not particularly receptive to non-specialist views on their subject-matters, the authors recommend avoiding a top-down approach. They advocate for public participation via genuine dialogue.</p>

<p>I wonder what venues could be used for that? In my experience, science museums provide a great venue for this kind of engagement (if you are in the area, the Boston Museum of Science is great!), but perhaps tend to be a wee too focused on younger audiences. Maybe universities and publicly funded labs (like American Federally Funded R&amp;D Centers - “FFRDCs”) could host “open-house” events for the public more often? I wonder if promoting some “ask your friendly neighborhood physicist” - or whichever scientific specialization! - event at a local library could become a thing. With canapés? I hear <a href="https://astronomyontap.org/">Astronomy on Tap</a> are also great events.</p>

<p>On point 4, the authors are a bit roundabout</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><em>”[minority mistrust] may affect considerations of scientific evidence in policymaking, as well as decisions by individuals that can affect society at large.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We can be a bit more explicit - of course, no judgment on different opinions - and name some examples of what they may have meant: policies where the attitudes of few can cause exponentially broader effects include vaccination and mask use during a pandemic. Situations where the voice of minorities take disproportional size in policy making include the effect of hate discourse that at times empowers extremist governments. The effect of policymaking in science is a reality for me and many of my friends, who have been living through the “Brazilian scientific diaspora” of the past 10-20 years (yes, this is a thing! If you have not heard of it, read more  <a href="https://cbreuc.org/about/#:~:text=Researches%20indicate%20that%2C%20since%20the,called%20the%20%E2%80%9CScientific%20Diaspora%E2%80%9D">here</a>).</p>

<p>Point 5 raises more intriguing questions. The conclusions for this point are based on Figure 5 of the paper. Let me reproduce it:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Perceived_scientific_priorities.png" alt="image-center" class="align-center" style="width: 60%;" /></p>

<p>This graph showcases the difference in perception the public has on “what science aims at” as a research topic and “how much should it prioritize” the given topic. Four subjects are considered: healthcare, energy, poverty reduction, and military/defense.</p>

<p>A first question comes to my mind: how much society prioritizes and is interested in simple discovery? Unfortunately, the plot above misses the topic of non-applied scientific inquiry. That is what drives the majority of my colleagues in the physical sciences, at least. While of little direct social relevance, at first sight, this topic contributes to people’s <a href="https://www.ibsafoundation.org/en/blog/culture-and-health/insights/towards-cultural-welfare">“cultural welfare”</a>. Looking at the stars and knowing that Earth is not the center of the universe has had profound impacts in society (at least regarding Western society, I guess we can say). Learning that genes encode many of our traits is important for predicting and treating genetic disorders, but it also gives us a better sense on ethical decisions and our general ability to deal with our personal similarities and differences. These pieces of knowledge affect our homes, families, and how we deal with each other. I would be very curious to see how an extended statistical analysis would position the matter in reference with the others in Figure 5.</p>

<p>Now, are scientists engaged enough in policymaking and working too much in military applications? I guess the answer depends on the country, as the authors also hint, and these points may be somewhat related. In the USA, agencies traditionally related with science (NSF, DOE, DARPA, IARPA) have open and constant channels of communications with researchers, both public and private. Only agencies like DARPA and IARPA do have defense applications as a priority. Direct connections with congress people and senators is perhaps a bit rarer in my experience. I have seen it happen if personal contacts exist, but building those channels is not easy.</p>

<p>I have been terribly lucky in my past few years at Boston, as there is a strong community of thinkers in the area. Events promoted by Science Technology and Society (at times known as STS) clubs and students at Harvard and MIT have been helping me bridge science and policymaking, introducing players and consultants that work directly or indirectly in D.C.. On the other hand, a recurring theme, reinforced by my acquaintances more closely associated with active members of the federal government, is the challenge of capturing their attention with topics considered non-immediate. This is particularly true for subjects unrelated to defense. So in the case of the USA, if there is a public perception that scientists have been prioritizing defense activities too much, perhaps this could be a result of political pressures.</p>

<p>On a bright side, my experience with local government has been quite positive! I have seen, and participated in, several public-private science-centered initiatives to promote economic development. This kind of work may, perhaps, help diminish the gap between “science aim” and “scientists priority” in what regards reducing proverty. Of course, similar initiatives exist at the federal level as well, particularly focused on manufacturing of tech (which I guess always require strong scientific foundations).</p>

<p>Perhaps my alignment of interests makes this a self-serving satisfaction, but I am happy to see this subject being advanced by hard data-driven scientific work! So I will leave my sincere appreciation to Dr. Cologna and her collaborators, and wish them all luck with their refereeing process, which will undoubtedly enhance the scientific value of their work.</p>

<p>I should also thank my wife, for pointing out to me the Nature News in the first place!</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While I was working on a much more technical first post, Nature released a News article on a core raison-d’être of this blog: the trust of public in scientists, scientist engagement with policy making, and their involvement with society. So, let’s take this opportunity to delve into this topic.]]></summary></entry></feed>