<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-15T14:36:24-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pedro Lopes’s</title><subtitle>My professional website and blog. Come here for news and discussions on physics, scientific management and leadership, and sustainable lifestyle.</subtitle><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><entry><title type="html">Improving How Universities Teach</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/11/15/Improving_how_universities_teach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving How Universities Teach" /><published>2025-11-15T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2025-11-15T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/11/15/Improving_how_universities_teach</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/11/15/Improving_how_universities_teach.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="book-review--improving-how-universities-teach-science-carl-wieman">Book Review – <em>Improving How Universities Teach Science</em> (Carl Wieman)</h2>

<p>Been a while since our last book review at <em>Set Physics to Stun</em>! Maybe a bit lazy on my side, but this one is getting reviewed even though I didn’t strictly finish it. The reason is simple: the book is excellent, my wife has now claimed it as her next read, and I am a slow bus reader. So I’ll collect my wins, write down what I got from it, and pass the baton (and the book) on.</p>

<p>The book in question is <a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/books/9780674972070"><em>Improving How Universities Teach Science</em></a>, by AMO physicist turned education scientist — and Nobel Prize winner — Carl Wieman.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="my-history-with-the-wieman-initiative">My history with the Wieman initiative</h3>

<p>My connection to Wieman’s work on science education goes back to my postdoc days at UBC. I was lucky enough to be exposed to a program that trained postdocs and young faculty on modern, research-based teaching methods, offered by UBC’s Center for Teaching and Learning as part of the final years of the <a href="https://cwsei.ubc.ca/">Carl Wieman Science Education Initiative (CWSEI)</a>.</p>

<p>That experience was eye-opening. It showed me:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Clear, stubborn data that our traditional lecture-based teaching is largely ineffective.</li>
  <li>How domain experts are usually <em>actually</em> unskilled at transmitting their knowledge efficiently.</li>
  <li>That teaching can be treated as a research problem: hypothesis, evidence, iteration, improvement.</li>
</ul>

<p>Reading <em>Improving How Universities Teach Science</em> years later felt a bit like seeing the “director’s commentary” for the initiative that shaped how I think about teaching.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="what-the-book-is-about">What the book is about</h3>

<p>On the surface, this can be a somewhat dry book: it’s about university structures, funding, departmental politics, and long-term institutional change. But if, like me, you care about:</p>

<ul>
  <li>how we train future scientists and engineers,</li>
  <li>how big institutions actually change (or don’t), and</li>
  <li>how to bring evidence into teaching, not just research,</li>
</ul>

<p>then it becomes a very rich read. Again, it helped me to have an insider’s context.</p>

<p>Wieman uses UBC and CU Boulder as the main case studies to show how he and his collaborators designed and implemented a large-scale science education initiative to modernize how science and engineering are taught. The book doubles as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A post-mortem of a real, well-managed organizational change project in big universities.</li>
  <li>A practical guide to the administrative inner workings of departments and faculties.</li>
  <li>A curated entry point into both <strong>management literature</strong> and <strong>evidence-based education research</strong> in the context of scientific environments.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="why-change-science-teaching-at-all">Why change science teaching at all?</h3>

<p>One of the big-picture frames of the book is historical. Wieman reminds us that university missions have drifted:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Before WWII, universities were largely teaching-focused, with students as the primary stakeholders.</li>
  <li>Post-WWII, massive research funding reshaped institutions to prioritize research, with nations and global competitiveness becoming central stakeholders.</li>
</ul>

<p>Teaching never fully caught up with this shift. In many places, it became something we <em>assume</em> will happen “naturally” if you put clever people with PhDs in front of a classroom.</p>

<p>At the same time, student demographics are changing, funding mechanisms are in flux, and the role of universities in society is being questioned from all directions. Under those conditions, relying on traditional, intuition-based teaching methods is not just inefficient — it’s irresponsible.</p>

<p>The Science Education Initiative (SEI) that Wieman describes sets out to change this, by trying to <strong>change teaching culture</strong>: its values, beliefs, and everyday practices. Crucially, it does this by borrowing from the <em>research</em> culture that scientists already respect.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="what-made-the-sei-work">What made the SEI work?</h3>

<p>Wieman argues that the SEI’s relative success hinged on a few design choices:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Driven by faculty, not imposed on them.</strong>
Departments had to want to participate and had internal champions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Clear measures of success.</strong>
The initiative emphasized measurable learning outcomes and concrete changes in courses, not just vague “innovation” or “awareness.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Real incentives, both individual and departmental.</strong>
Incentives were tied to educational outcomes and visible improvements, not just to writing reports or attending workshops.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This is a recurring theme in the book: if you want real change, you need to treat teaching improvement with the same seriousness, resourcing, and rigor that we reserve for research.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="management-theory-rogers-kotter-and-beyond">Management theory: Rogers, Kotter, and beyond</h3>

<p>One of my favorite aspects of the book is how openly Wieman leans on existing management and change literature, instead of reinventing everything from scratch.</p>

<h4 id="everett-rogers--how-innovation-spreads">Everett Rogers – how innovation spreads</h4>

<p>Wieman uses Everett Rogers’ framework for how innovations are adopted:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>knowledge (awareness) → persuasion (learn more) → decision (weigh benefits/costs) → implementation (try it) → confirmation (keep or abandon)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If adoption fails at any stage, the later stages never happen. This sounds obvious, but in practice we often try to “train faculty in active learning” without checking whether they’re even past the <em>persuasion</em> stage.</p>

<p>He also discusses the classic categories — <em>innovators, early adopters, early majority, late majority, laggards</em> — and points out their limits for pedagogy. Real faculty members don’t sit neatly in one bucket:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Someone might be an early adopter of clickers but resistant to changing exams.</li>
  <li>Others might move painfully slowly at first, then adopt new teaching approaches very broadly once they’re convinced.</li>
</ul>

<p>It’s a nice reminder that people are more complex than diffusion-of-innovation cartoons.</p>

<h4 id="john-kotter--how-organizations-change">John Kotter – how organizations change</h4>

<p>From John Kotter’s work on organizational change, Wieman borrows several key ideas and puts numbers on them:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Change needs a one-time, limited-duration infusion of resources.</strong>
It’s more expensive to <em>change</em> practices and culture than to maintain them later.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Funding must match the scale of change.</strong>
The literature suggests investing around <strong>5–10% of a unit’s annual budget for ~5 years</strong> to meaningfully change culture.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In the SEI case, that translated to something like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>~$400k per department per year</li>
  <li>≈ $2M per department over 5 years</li>
  <li>≈ $10M to transform teaching in 5 departments</li>
  <li>Affecting ~25–30 regularly offered courses per department</li>
</ul>

<p>This is <strong>10–100 times larger</strong> than the typical early-2000s grants for “improving teaching”.</p>

<p>The strategy was also selective: change a core majority of departments deeply, and let those become the gravitational center that helps pull the rest of the institution along. Both UBC and CU Boulder ran <strong>competitive internal grant programs</strong> for departments to participate.</p>

<p>If you’ve ever wondered why most “small teaching grants” don’t move the needle much on institutional culture, this book gives a brutally clear answer: they’re simply not at the right scale.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="science-education-specialists-the-hidden-engine">Science Education Specialists: the hidden engine</h3>

<p>A large and very interesting part of the book is dedicated to <strong>Science Education Specialists (SES)</strong> — a role that didn’t really exist before the SEI.</p>

<p>These are usually domain experts (e.g., physicists, chemists, biologists) with a genuine interest in education, hired specifically to work within departments and courses to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>help redesign curricula and course materials,</li>
  <li>collect and analyze data on student learning,</li>
  <li>coach faculty on evidence-based strategies.</li>
</ul>

<p>Wieman doesn’t spend endless pages profiling individuals, but he does give a helpful summary of the skills SESs needed and were trained in. It doubles as a great crash course in what “evidence-based teaching” actually entails:</p>

<ul>
  <li>effect of prior knowledge</li>
  <li>knowledge organization: expert vs. novice</li>
  <li>motivation</li>
  <li>learning and transfer</li>
  <li>deliberate practice</li>
  <li>development of self-directed learners</li>
  <li>learning goals</li>
  <li>formative assessment</li>
  <li>memory and retention</li>
  <li>peer instruction and effective clicker use</li>
  <li>group work</li>
  <li>characteristics of expert tutors</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’re new to this area, that list alone is a powerful pointer map. Many of these topics — especially <strong>motivation</strong>, deliberate practice, and how experts differ from novices — overlap with recurring themes here at <em>Set Physics to Stun</em>, especially when we talk about scientific management and mentoring.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="why-this-book-matters-even-if-you-dont-run-a-department">Why this book matters (even if you don’t run a department)</h3>

<p>You don’t need to be a dean or a department chair to get value from <em>Improving How Universities Teach Science</em>. I’d particularly recommend it if you are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>a <strong>faculty member</strong> who wants to improve teaching but is tired of vague advice,</li>
  <li>a <strong>postdoc or grad student</strong> curious about how teaching reform actually works at scale,</li>
  <li>a <strong>science manager, program director, or center lead</strong> who thinks about organizational change.</li>
</ul>

<p>For me, the book serves several roles at once:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A reminder that teaching improvement is a <em>serious</em> project worth serious resources.</li>
  <li>A concrete case study of change that respects both <strong>research culture</strong> and <strong>educational evidence</strong>.</li>
  <li>A source of references and mental models I can bring into my own work as a mentor, collaborator, and occasional agitator for better practices.</li>
</ul>

<p>So that’s it — a brief tour of the parts of <em>Improving How Universities Teach Science</em> that resonated most with me. I hope this motivates some of you to pick up the book as well (and maybe finish it before your spouse steals it).</p>

<p>If more of us — as mentors, individual contributors, and administrators — start treating teaching with the same rigor and seriousness as we treat research, I’d say Wieman’s project, and this book, will have done their job.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review – Improving How Universities Teach Science (Carl Wieman)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dysfunctionality on scientific teams</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/29/team_dysfunctions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dysfunctionality on scientific teams" /><published>2025-04-29T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2025-04-29T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/04/29/team_dysfunctions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/29/team_dysfunctions.html"><![CDATA[<p>Back to book reviews! The backlog is growing!</p>

<p>Last year, I read a lot about management, trying to educate myself more on the topic and to connect with the lives of—and challenges faced by—scientists. In September 2024, I posted about the factors driving an individual’s motivation in a scientific team; the discussion was framed as a review of the book “<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/drive-the-surprising-truth-about-what-motivates-us_daniel-h-pink/246588/?resultid=f8f87171-a9f2-404a-9610-3ab7705fcda7#edition=5980628&amp;idiq=3847557">Drive</a>”, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_H._Pink">Daniel H. Pink</a>. This time we will expand the scope and consider what makes a team work well together. The inspiration for this post comes from reading <a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/overcoming-the-five-dysfunctions-of-a-team-a-field-guide-for-leaders-managers-and-facilitators_patrick-lencioni/253041/?resultid=158b6959-06a2-4a80-82e5-775e96c66d1d#edition=4547621&amp;idiq=1654363">The Five Dysfunctions of a Team</a> by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Lencioni">Patrick Lencioni</a>.</p>

<p>The author is a well-known figure in private industry, coaching companies on organizational health and teamwork. He has written several books, many widely acclaimed. So, we should probably start with a disclaimer: the “sociological” theories in the book have found deep appreciation among several leaders and corporations, and have been built upon the author’s empirical experience—but, to my knowledge, they have not been rigorously tested using scientific methods. Still, human experience is quite valuable, and the thoughts in the book definitely got me thinking.</p>

<p>The Five Dysfunctions of a Team is mostly composed of a long story in which the author role-plays (a common practice in business training, I’ve come to learn) characters navigating team conflict within a company. They are somewhat saved—or at least set on a path toward progress—by a new CEO who has mastered the concepts behind team dysfunction. The author then re-describes these ideas in detail. The five dysfunctions are presented in a causal relationship, where each layer serves as a scaffold for the next:</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/dysfunctionality_pyramid.png" title="team dysfunctionality pyramid">
          <img src="/assets/images/dysfunctionality_pyramid.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>Again with the disclaimer that this was not presented as a scientifically verified psychological process, I gotta say I can quite relate to this perspective.</p>

<p>Looking at modern science in general, it’s rare for individuals to work entirely alone. They exist, but they don’t represent most of the statistics. In my own scientific collaborations—and from observing those of colleagues—I’ve often seen teams exhibit some degree of dysfunction that can fits the pattern above. Here are some signatures that some may relate to:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>invulnerability</em>: defensive behavior when criticism to one’s results - calculations, data, analyses - are raised, lack of attention during appointments</li>
  <li><em>artificial harmony</em>: researchers lower in the hierarchy ceasing to communicate with supervisors; researchers higher in the hierarchy ignoring contact with trainees and direct reports for long periods of time; not communicating mispace of production rate</li>
  <li><em>ambiguity</em>: extended timelines to produce results, projects that never finish, repeatedly rescheduled meetings, spacing out during meetings and not recording action items</li>
  <li><em>low standards</em>: lack of interest in reviewing write-ups, careless attention to one’s own or others’ technical results, lack of initiative</li>
  <li><em>status and ego</em>: pursuit of self-interested endeavors or priorities without transparency; griping; judging</li>
</ul>

<p>I hope the language above makes it clear that these examples are not biased toward any particular group of scientists: they can occur among trainees and students, managers and supervisors, and in virtually any field of science.</p>

<p>What is the onset of these dysfunctions? The author doesn’t say much about how they begin, and I believe that characterizing early warning signs of dysfunction—or signs that a team is headed down that path—could be very important. In science, I dare say much of this can arise from overcommitment to too many activities. The workload of science managers can be extreme, and the path of individual contributors often resembles a random walk. Haste and pressure can lead to mismanagement and miscommunication. The often present high degree of freedom in scientific environments, without proper management, can also easily lead to ambiguities and individualism.</p>

<p>The author also emphasizes (in a good attempt to sell another of his books) that not all people are capable of being team players, and that paying attention to certain virtues can help in hiring and fostering more productive behaviors. I don’t feel too comfortable to judge what others can or cannot do, but I think I see where the author is coming from, and I guess I like the advice.</p>

<p>On the pathway to solving such dysfunctions, the author highlights the importance of humility (“the most precious virtue and antidote for all sin”), which enables vulnerability and creates the possibility of trust among human beings—who he sees as naturally inclined to self-protection. If the pyramid model above holds, a approach to fix the problem is to erode it from the base—by entering into risky discomfort and building trust.</p>

<p>My backlog of book reviews is getting large. I hope I can make a dent in it. This year I’m moving my reading interests from management to philosophy of science, and it looks like reading will be slower; since the content is much denser, I may post revisions by chapter. In any case, stay tuned for more lessons learned from the literature!</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back to book reviews! The backlog is growing!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boston on a budget</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/03/22/Boston_groceries.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boston on a budget" /><published>2025-03-22T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-22T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/03/22/Boston_groceries</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/03/22/Boston_groceries.html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a long one in the making. I should dedicate it to my wife, as this has been a family project running for years. We will divert from science management for this issue, and talk about grocery management! So a post on data science for everyone!</p>

<p>Here is a short prelude to a longer story: back in the covid years, my wife and I were living in Vancouver, and dealing with the steep prices of the city on academic salaries. Given we love cooking, for fun (and maybe out of spite as well), we started hacking the city for grocery bargains. We were very successful and, by the time we were about to leave to Boston (our current residence), I told a friend - whose identity I will spare, to not gloat too much! - that we seemed to be spending about $20 bucks a week in groceries for two people. He called me a liar (or just plain wrong). He underestimated my scientific spirit; he didn’t know what he was starting.</p>

<h3 id="nerd-sniping-strikes-back"><em>NERD-sniping strikes back</em></h3>

<p>Boston, like Vancouver, is one of the worst cities in the world (and in particular in the US) for cost of living. Here goes an illustrative chart on that:</p>

<figure class="align-center" style="width: 70%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/country_overview.png" title="US cost of living overview">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/country_overview.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>The motivation to hack Boston groceries was there for me and my wife, just like in Vancouver, and I was determined to get revanche on my friend who doubted me. So we decided to go quantitative. Since our first week in Boston, we started a spreadsheet where we have registered every single grocery purchase we ever made (focused on foodstuffs only). Fast-forward 3.5 years and we have over 1000 entries of data!</p>

<figure class="align-right" style="width: 40%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/spreadsheet_overview.png" title="Spreadsheet overview">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/spreadsheet_overview.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>
<p>Plenty for our scientific minds to have fun with.</p>

<p><em>A small disclaimer: Boston scientific culture is cramed with opportunities for free food (both in academia and industry settings). Given that, we are very mindful about cooking most of what we eat, not having more than one free meal per week, on average, and not going to restaurants mode than once a month (not a challenge; Boston’s restaurant’s scene is surprisingly not that exciting). These free meals and restaurant food expenses are not accounted for. What we account is just what is spent in pure grocery shopping, which by far and large accounts for most of our monthly expenses other than bills/rent.</em></p>

<p>The database accounts for names of the items, quantity purchased, price and price per quantity (“specific price” or “Sprice”), date, place, and category. We also included a details column for any noteworthy comments we felt like making. Keeping format and units through quantities is not always easy, and every now and then we have to review the database for drifts in patterns. That introduces a degree of uncertainty in the data which, since our dataset is so large and mostly coherently populated, is likely to be inconsequent to the truthfulness of broad conclusions on our patterns.</p>

<p>So let’s look at interesting general insights that we believe can be quite meaningful to the typical Bostonian. And also some personal insights we learned about our on consumer patterns.</p>

<h3 id="good-grocery-deals-and-where-do-we-find-them"><em>Good grocery deals and where do we find them</em></h3>

<p>Let’s start with some exemplary photographs of what a grocery day can look like.</p>

<figure class="align-center" style="width: 70%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/grocery_day_examples.png" title="Grocery day examples">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/grocery_day_examples.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>
<p>As can be seen, good deals can include vegetables and fruits, as much as meats and packaged ingredients. The secret here is that this city (as perhaps many in the USA) deal with too much abundance, and the surplus market can lead to unbelievable deals (like 30+ lemons for $1).</p>

<p>Our data allows us to carefully consider where do we go most for purchases and draw some geographic correlations. We live in the North End neighborhood, which is fairly central and well connected. 4-5 different stores concentrate the majority of our expenses. We found out that <em>we are lazy, but not that much</em>. We certainly visit markets and stores closer to us more often than far, but we actually put the effort to reach some farther destinations because their deals are special to us. Quantitatively (data not shown), we do groceries within a couple km from our home about 85% of the time, but out of the remaining 15%, almost its totality brings us to about full 5km away from where we live (and we got no cars).</p>

<figure class="align-center" style="width: 70%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/market_map.png" title="Boston market map">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/market_map.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>On the graph above we show some of our favorite items for each place. Some may be unexpected: Whole Foods, generally the most expensive market short of gourmet markets, is the place where we can get “natural” peanut - no sugar or oils added, unfortunately it is hard to also avoid salt here in the US - for the best price. It is a special item that we care for just like that, so we suffer Whole Foods every now and then. An interesting finding is also that large chain stores may not have standardized prices even within a single city. A small corner Target store at Beacon Hill, my wife realized, used to sell full 12-egg cartons for $1! Well, that was back in 2022. Regulations on granaries made that go away, but we enjoyed the deal while it lasted! They still sell milk for the best prices.</p>

<p>Other favorite places for us include the traditional Haymarket and Jia Ho market - the latter in China Town - for surplus fruits and veggies, as well as the hispanic market Tropical Foods in Roxbury, for flours and meat (particularly chicken) and some other specialty items.</p>

<h3 id="expense-records"><em>Expense records</em></h3>

<p>Dear friend that doubted me, this one is for you! You know who you are! ;-)</p>

<figure class="align-right" style="width: 50%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/expenses_weekly.png" title="Weekly expenses analysis">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/expenses_weekly.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>Knowing the right places for the right items, eating mostly home prepped food, and putting the energy to pursue the right deals, we have hit our mark! Averaging through our whole time in Boston, we have spent, on average, close to $25 per week! In fact, averaging our weekly expenses per year, we found that we considerably lowered our expenses as time passed (and despite significant inflation). In recent years (data not shown), we are spending around $19/week on groceries. (for the purists that may not be satisfied with the $25 above, given my original claim while in Vancouver)</p>

<figure class="align-right" style="width: 50%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/categorized_expenses.png" title="Categorized expenses">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/categorized_expenses.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>The data suggests all kinds of other interesting patterns, including some degree of periodicity (which we associate with our consuming rate of more industrialized products like condiments and seasonings). Looking at our categorized expenses, it seems like we do pretty well; grains, dairy, vegetables and fruits make bulk expenses, with meat - which is considerably more expensive - matching values, suggesting we don’t buy much meat (even when we do, we tend to go for items usually ignored/discarded by most, like chicken gizzards and beef/pork bones).</p>

<h3 id="seasonal-and-other-chronological-patterns"><em>Seasonal and other chronological patterns</em></h3>

<p>With our data, we can also track how inflation and public policies have affected the prices of different items. A couple favorites are milk and eggs, the former because it is such a staple item for us, and the latter because of having shown a fourfold increase in price through our years of monitoring.</p>

<figure class="half ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/milk_per_galon.png" title="milk per galon">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/milk_per_galon.png" alt="milk" />
      </a>
    
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/eggs_per_dozen.png" title="eggs per dozen">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/eggs_per_dozen.png" alt="eggs" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>A curious one involves looking at the seasonality of our consumption of fruits. Comparing 4 sub-categories showcases that our purchase pattern (which, take me for my word, follows the best deals we find) is strongly correlated with the seasons for each of these major fruit categories. Surprisingly pears appear to fall out of the line, with peak in our purchases in April. Some explanations for this could include that good deals for pears in that time of the year may involve importing them from the southern hemisphere. Another option would be that, given that pears are generally available throughout the whole year, and late fall in the northern hemisphere is not a good season for any of our major purchase sub-categories, we may default to pears which we like so much!</p>

<h3 id="the-economy-of-scale"><em>The economy of scale</em></h3>

<p>A commonly shared intuition is that buying foodstuffs in larger quantities result in economy. But is that the case? If so, what is the scaling law?</p>

<p>I don’t hide from anyone my admiration for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allometry">allometry</a>, so trying to verify a financial - for the lack of opportunity to do biophysical studies - scaling law was a real temptation. Scatter plotting all our purchases with respect to the corresponding quantities bought (normalized to unitless values) gives us direct access to exactly that knowledge!</p>

<figure class="align-right" style="width: 50%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/fruit_seasonality.png" title="Fruit seasonality">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/fruit_seasonality.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>Indeed, a descending trend is verified on price as function of quantity. A fit showcases that the corresponding scaling law shown for our dataset is $price \sim quantity^{-1.0 \pm 0.1}$!</p>

<figure class="align-right" style="width: 50%;">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/price_quantity_correlations.png" title="Price-quantity correlation">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/price_quantity_correlations.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>This is an awesome but bittersweet result. Some of us (me!) were really hoping for a non-linear inverse scaling that favored even lower prices for ever larger quantities. We just got inverse proportionality. We did a brief analysis separating quantities measured by volume in separate of weight or units, and the scaling laws do vary; but we lack more data to verify trends with more certainty when we categorize like that. In any case, we find it is awesome to see common knowledge verified and quantified!</p>

<h3 id="final-words"><em>Final words</em></h3>

<p>Given how expensive central cities are becoming, and given how short student stipends can be, I hope this knowledge can come in handy for many folks, including scientists in the making. The ideas can be replicated in other cities or, if you live in Boston, you may want to deploy them according to your own needs and preferences!</p>

<p>Often I see professional chefs saying that good food depends on quality ingredients. My experience is that cooking is a forgiving science and a multi-sensorial art. If your tomato is not perfectly round, you can still make good pizza sauce, salad, or whatnot. You can make it look good, smell good, and be very appealing. So let it not be said that the use of economy of scale, surplus markets, and undervalued ingredients will limit the quality of what we eat. I will leave you with some photos of what we have cooked, to make our final point, and some words of excitement!</p>

<figure class="half ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/final_outcome.png" title="Final outcome">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/final_outcome.png" alt="end game" />
      </a>
    
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/boston_data/close-up_message.png" title="Close-up message">
          <img src="/assets/images/boston_data/close-up_message.png" alt="close-up" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a long one in the making. I should dedicate it to my wife, as this has been a family project running for years. We will divert from science management for this issue, and talk about grocery management! So a post on data science for everyone!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Behavior can be learned</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/17/behavior_can_be_learned.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Behavior can be learned" /><published>2025-02-17T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/17/behavior_can_be_learned</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/17/behavior_can_be_learned.html"><![CDATA[<p>Short post inspired by a big lesson. Recently I was in a conference and me and other scientists were discussing how easy or hard it was to get strong performers in a scientific team depending on different environments. One of our colleagues, well-intentioned, mentioned that his organization didn’t always get the most committed performers, but every-now-and-then they would find a gem that could move forward quite independently.</p>

<p>At this point, another of our colleagues - who deserves praise for educating us all, so thanks Alex Cooper-Roy - interjected. Paraphrasing, he reminded us that commitment and dedication to a cause or a project are behavioural traits and behaviour can be learned. So instead of selecting contributors according to how they innately behave as we expect, perhaps we should spend more time fostering those behaviors. Communicating clearly what are our expectations, affirmatively supporting behaviors that are aligned with those expectations, providing constructive feedback when they are not aligned. A good lesson for science managers: “behaviour can be learned”. Thanks again Alex!</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Short post inspired by a big lesson. Recently I was in a conference and me and other scientists were discussing how easy or hard it was to get strong performers in a scientific team depending on different environments. One of our colleagues, well-intentioned, mentioned that his organization didn’t always get the most committed performers, but every-now-and-then they would find a gem that could move forward quite independently.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Words of Wisdom #2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/19/WoW_Serge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Words of Wisdom #2" /><published>2025-01-19T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/19/WoW_Serge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/19/WoW_Serge.html"><![CDATA[<p>What better way to start the new year than with <em>Words of Wisdom</em>? For the second installment of our blog series featuring interviews with science managers, we welcome Dr. Serge Moore. Serge is the manager of Québec’s Laboratory of Environmental Testing at Environment and Climate Change Canada. He oversees one of Canada’s five environmental toxicology and forensic chemistry laboratories, focusing on water metal content analysis across much of Ontario’s eastern border. Beyond his PhD in Chemistry from Université de Montréal, Serge is skilled in electronics, computer programming, and even woodworking.</p>

<p>In this edition of WoW, we explore the challenges and unique aspects of managing science in the public sector.</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> What would you say are the main challenges of scientific work in a public-sector non-academic space? How do you contrast it with academia or industry?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SM:</em> In my experience, politics and public opinion significantly influence the scientist’s work—decisions on how to use results, whether to publish them, or even what to focus on. While similar dynamics exist in academia and industry, the public sector is particularly vulnerable to changes in government leadership. These shifts introduce additional layers of complexity that can take decision-making out of scientists’ hands.</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> What would you say is harder to fund in public-sector research: infrastructure or sustained operations/projects?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SM:</em> This depends on definitions. We distinguish among infrastructure, capital, operational, and human resources:</p>
<ul class="notice--info">
  <li><em>Infrastructure:</em> Buildings and general assets not directly related to specific scientific equipment. These often have decent budgets, especially when safety or security improvements are needed.</li>
  <li><em>Capital expenditures:</em> High-value instruments or equipment. Funding for new instrumentation is particularly challenging.</li>
  <li><em>Operational budgets:</em> Consumables and tools needed to run equipment. These budgets are typically fixed and rarely increase, one of the reasons why new instruments are hard to fund.</li>
  <li><em>Human resources:</em> Team headcounts, which are significantly influenced by political factors.</li>
</ul>

<p class="notice--info">In my daily work, the hardest to fund (in order) are operational &gt; capital &gt; human resources &gt; infrastructure. However, circumstances can shift—for example, human resources can sometimes be particularly difficult to secure.</p>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> How do you view motivation? What keeps a scientific team motivated?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SM:</em> Two main aspects come to mind—practical and professional.</p>
<ul class="notice--info">
  <li><em>Practical:</em> Flexible working hours are incredibly impactful, particularly for employees managing family responsibilities.</li>
  <li><em>Professional:</em> Helping employees feel proud of their work. This is especially important for specialists—for example, someone deeply knowledgeable about fish toxicology can become highly attached to their contributions. Respect and recognition go a long way in maintaining motivation.</li>
</ul>

<p class="notice--warning"><em>SPTS:</em> What pitfalls have you observed in your career that you’d advise junior scientific managers to avoid?</p>

<p class="notice--info"><em>SM:</em> The most important advice is to consistently self-reflect and understand your ambitions. The public sector has strict rules to ensure information is accessible to everyone, which can help employees navigate their career progression. However, climbing the ranks is often opportunistic, so timing is also critical. While this may not be a direct pitfall, being mindful of it is essential for long-term success.</p>

<p>That is it! Thanks Serge for your <em>Words of Wisdom</em>! <em>Set Physics to Stun</em> hears you!</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What better way to start the new year than with Words of Wisdom? For the second installment of our blog series featuring interviews with science managers, we welcome Dr. Serge Moore. Serge is the manager of Québec’s Laboratory of Environmental Testing at Environment and Climate Change Canada. He oversees one of Canada’s five environmental toxicology and forensic chemistry laboratories, focusing on water metal content analysis across much of Ontario’s eastern border. Beyond his PhD in Chemistry from Université de Montréal, Serge is skilled in electronics, computer programming, and even woodworking.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pão de Queijo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/15/pao_de_queijo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pão de Queijo" /><published>2024-12-15T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/15/pao_de_queijo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/15/pao_de_queijo.html"><![CDATA[<p>Through fall season, Harvard hosts a Science &amp; Cooking course, where science topics relevant for cooking such as soft matter, organic chemistry, heat transport, and diffusion, are discussed. This course is often accompanied by a series of public lectures working as an outreach activity to engage the lay community.</p>

<p>In this public lecture series, reputed chefs are brought to a stage shared with a physics or chemistry Harvard instructor (at times known as a preceptor…Harvard culture has funny local jargon for reasonable widespread terms…), and the audience is stimulated to participate and engage in various ways. This year, in particular, the instructors of the course opened the opportunity for audience participants to share term papers and join in the course science fair with the students actually taking the full class.</p>

<p>Well, I am into cooking, and into science, and into challenges. So me, my wife and a friend (who all share some of these passions) decided to get together and pursue a small joint project. So for the first bona fide science post of Set Physics to Stun, I bring you the project we submitted to the class and science fair. The results were built on some good 10 hours of efforts in a kitchen and analyzing data on recipes for Brazilian pão de queijo.</p>

<h1 id="harvard-science--cooking-pão-de-queijo-and-the-tough-crust">Harvard Science &amp; Cooking: Pão de queijo and the tough crust</h1>

<p><em>Lisa Lin, Pedro Lopes, Marianne Moore</em></p>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In a cook-out get-together in October 2024, the present authors attempted a pão de queijo recipe from Alex Atala [1]. While the cheese puffs tasted fine, the texture of the crust did not correspond to the memories of one author who grew up in Brazil; the breads felt too dry, and the crusts too thick. Following the Harvard’s Science and Cooking public lecture series a few weeks later, we were led to consider the effects of heat (water) diffusion into (out of) pão de queijo, and what factors might govern its texture.</p>

<p>Though pão de queijo is naturally gluten-free and uses only tapioca starch, we found evidence suggesting that the varieties of tapioca starch used could be relevant. Most commonly mentioned were the effects of using sweet (unfermented) versus sour (fermented; polvilho azedo, henceforth referred to as azedo) tapioca starch, with the former contributing to denser crumb and the latter to a more open and elastic crumb [2][3]. In our original recipe, we used a mix of azedo (from Brazil) and sweet tapioca starch from Thailand (henceforth referred to as Thai starch), and some references also claimed a noticeable difference between sweet Thai tapioca starch and sweet tapioca starch produced in Brazil (polvilho doce, henceforth referred to as doce)[4]. Though this author attributed the result to the fineness of the milling, tapioca starch does not contain broken-down grains like regular flour, but rather just semi-crystalline granules of amylose and amylopectin that are typically extracted by filtering out any solids from the cassava root itself [5]. Despite having different textures, we believe that a more meaningful difference between Thai and Brazilian starches could be at play.</p>

<p>Rather than milling, we believe hydration plays a more significant role in the difference between Thai and Brazilian tapioca starches. In particular, the latter has a moisture content of around 45% [6], leading to its characteristic granularity in contrast to the fine texture of the former, which typically has a moisture content of around 13% [7]. One of the authors knows from experience that, upon further hydration, sifted Thai starch can be substituted for doce to good effect in recipes such as tapioca pancakes (beiju). Ref. [4] provides pictures comparing Brazilian cheese puffs made from Thai and azedo starches, but does not compare results using Thai and doce starches, leaving this hypothesis open to test. In wheat bread literature, the importance of starch gelatinization and retrogradation is well documented for different ingredients [8][9]. Given that the rise in bread is partially due to evaporation of water within the dough when exposed to heat, we expect that pão de queijo made from Brazilian tapioca starch, with its higher moisture content, will rise higher than pão made from Thai tapioca starch.</p>

<p>Pão de queijo has unquestionable popularity in its country of origin, Brazil, and this popularity is also growing internationally. Methodically applying a scientific empirical analysis on the controlling factors on the texture of this delicacy can help clarify and inform lovers of carby, cheesy goodness of how to tailor different aspects of any pão de queijo recipe to their own tastes. In this way we hope to advance the appreciation of this cultural heritage by diverse audiences worldwide.</p>

<h2 id="goals">Goals</h2>

<p>We investigate the effects of different ratios of sour to sweet tapioca starch on the thickness and texture of Brazilian cheese puff crusts. We also evaluate any potential discrepancies in the result by comparing Thai and Brazilian sweet tapioca flours.</p>

<h2 id="preliminaries-microscopy-imaging-of-starches">Preliminaries: Microscopy imaging of starches</h2>

<p>To give ourselves some intuition for how Thai and Brazilian tapioca starches would behave in a dough, we used bright-field microscopy to image the three starches we tested. The dry starch granules looked qualitatively identical at 10x magnification,, with perhaps lightly larger clumps in the doce starch (as could also be inferred by naked eye). On the other hand, mixing each starch with water in a ratio of 0.1 g starch : 200 ul tap water and imaging each sample on a glass slide covered with a cover slip revealed that the Thai brand starch granules absorbed water more uniformly than those of the Brazilian brands (1st image in right column, below), with kernels of undissolved starch still visible within the hydrated doce and azedo samples (2nd and 3rd images in right column, below). We thus expect doughs (and subsequent cheese breads) made from Thai starch to be smoother and softer than doughs made from Brazilian starch. In addition, granules of azedo flour tended to be least uniformly distributed throughout the liquid medium, leading us to expect the cheese breads made from azedo flour to be the driest and densest (as dense clumps would prevent the innermost starch granules from fully hydrating / gelatinizing).</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/microscopy.png" title="pao de queijo">
          <img src="/assets/images/microscopy.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>From top to bottom, samples of Thai sweet tapioca starch, Brazilian sweet tapioca starch (doce), and Brazilian sour tapioca starch (azedo). Left column: dry sample; right column: hydrated sample. Scale bars correspond to 20 um.</p>

<h2 id="base-recipe">Base recipe</h2>
<p>From Alex Atala’s YouTube channel [1].
Ingredients:</p>
<ul>
  <li>180 ml milk or water</li>
  <li>50 ml oil</li>
  <li>10 g salt</li>
  <li>200g sour tapioca starch</li>
  <li>130 g sweet tapioca starch</li>
  <li>1 egg</li>
  <li>300 g cheese</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="process">Process:</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Mix the tapioca starches together in a bowl.
    <ul>
      <li>Note: despite salt being part of the ingredient list, Atala misses describing adding salt at any step of the recipe</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Combine the milk and oil in a small pot and bring to a rolling boil.</li>
  <li>Pour this hot liquid into the dry mixture from Step 1 to pre-gelatinize the starch (scalding), adding liquid slowly while mixing to ensure homogeneity of pre-cooked starch
    <ul>
      <li>Note: starches start to gelatinize at 60ºC [1], [9]</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>When the dough is cool enough to handle, add in the egg and cheese (avoid cooking either ingredient in too hot dough). Knead into dough to combine.</li>
  <li>Allow the dough to rest for 20-30 minutes. Shape into balls.</li>
  <li>Bake at 200ºC for 15-20 minutes on the middle rack of the oven or until golden brown. Rotate the pan by 180º halfway through baking to ensure even browning.
    <ul>
      <li>We sprayed the tray with water before closing the oven door to delay crust setting and hoping to maximize dough expansion</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Let cheese breads cool for 10 minutes before cutting.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="test-recipe">Test recipe</h2>
<p><em>Constants:</em>
We keep the quantities of milk, oil, salt, cheese, and egg constant. We use whole milk, canola oil, a mixture of cheeses (mozzarella, Gruyere, and cheddar), and large white eggs (about 50g each). Like Atala, we did not add table salt. We use previously unopened bags of starch from the following brands: Amafil (doce and azedo starches) and Three Elephants (Thai).</p>

<p>Our process was followed in a kitchen at 54% humidity, and 17ºC. We used the same kitchen scale for all measurements, which has an uncertainty of 1g, and the same ruler, assuming an uncertainty of 0.1 cm. We did not measure the temperature of the oven.
Changing parameters:
We change the ratios of sour vs normal cassava starch and compare Asian starch vs brazilian starch for the sweet starch:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><em>labels:</em></th>
      <th><em>s</em></th>
      <th><em>ib</em></th>
      <th><em>ia</em></th>
      <th><em>iib</em></th>
      <th><em>iia</em></th>
      <th><em>iiib</em></th>
      <th><em>iiia</em></th>
      <th><em>ivb</em></th>
      <th><em>iva</em></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>sour brazilian</td>
      <td>100%</td>
      <td>75%</td>
      <td>75%</td>
      <td>50%</td>
      <td>50%</td>
      <td>25%</td>
      <td>25%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>sweet brazilian</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>25%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>50%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>75%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>100%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>sweet asian</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>25%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>50%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>75%</td>
      <td>0%</td>
      <td>100%</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The labels indicate the pure sour starch dough (s), the series made with a ratio of Asian sweet starch (a), and another series with Brazilian sweet starch (b).</p>

<h2 id="measurements-and-results">Measurements and Results</h2>
<p>At several steps of the process, we took different measurements on certain properties of the different doughs and analyzed them. The data we collected can be found in the following <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1WpC536jd9pG34yVvRRj4WgwT3N5eg3G1h8FI9-6dRLs/edit?usp=sharing">Data spreadsheet</a>.</p>

<h3 id="testing-hydration">Testing hydration:</h3>
<p>Is Asian tapioca starch less hydrated than Brazilian starch or is the difference in texture of the powders just a result of milling?</p>

<p>By comparing weight and volume, we can estimate differences in water content for each starch. We took 5 measurements of leveled (and uncompacted) 1 tablespoon of each type of starch and averaged them.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>1 tbsp of</th>
      <th>Asian starch (g)</th>
      <th>Brazilian sweet starch (g)</th>
      <th>Brazilian sour starch (g)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>8(1)</td>
      <td>10(1)</td>
      <td>10(1)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>8(1)</td>
      <td>9(1)</td>
      <td>9(1)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>7(1)</td>
      <td>10(1)</td>
      <td>10(1)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>8(1)</td>
      <td>9(1)</td>
      <td>9(1)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td>7(1)</td>
      <td>9(1)</td>
      <td>9(1)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Average</em></td>
      <td>7.6 (0.4)</td>
      <td>9.4(0.4)</td>
      <td>9.4(0.4)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Comparing the ratios of these average weights, we conclude that the Brazilian doce (sweet) starch is about 24% denser than the Thai starch. Though the Asian starch is finer in texture, the Brazilian one has more weight per volume, as one would expect for a higher water content in Brazilian doce flour. Assuming no difference in the original cassava species, we believe this indicates that the Brazilian sweet starch we chose is 24% more hydrated than the Asian one. This measurement corroborates our understanding that Brazilian tapioca starch is partially gelatinized and has a moisture content roughly 32% higher than Thai tapioca starch [8][9].</p>

<p>Note also that the density of the azedo (fermented) and doce Brazilian starches are the same. Assuming that the processing steps of these two starches are identical aside from additional fermentation of the azedo flour [10], then chemical changes from fermentation largely contribute only to differences in flavor of the starches.</p>

<h2 id="measurements-and-observations-at-each-step">Measurements and observations at each step</h2>

<p><em>Step 1.</em>
The Thai starch tended to clump together and stick to our measurement vessels, in contrast to the doce and azedo flours that did not compact together when measured and transferred between bowls. Jamming dynamics led Thai starch to often fly through the kitchen, across distances between approximately 5 - 10 cm.</p>

<p><em>Step 2.</em>
No flour mixing. No noteworthy observation.</p>

<p><em>Step 3.</em>
The scalding process felt different between samples from series “a” and series “b”. Generally, the doughs made from the Thai starch felt smoother and softer than those made from the sweet doce starch, which tended to be crumblier. The pure azedo batter, however, felt the crumbliest at this stage, as expected from our microscopy images.</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_1.png" title="pao de queijo">
          <img src="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_1.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p><em>A photo of the different doughs prepared; S stands for sour, A for Asian Sweet Starch, and B for Brazilian Sweet Starch. The upper row contains the doughs from series “a” and the lower one from series “b”. The doughy texture from series “a” at this stage can be clearly seen and contrasted with the series “b” in the lower row.</em></p>

<p><em>Step 4.</em>
While all samples became well-formed doughs at this stage, some of the observations above remain applicable here as well. The pure azedo dough was firmer than the others, while the dough made with pure Thai starch felt the softest and smoothest and was easily distinguishable from the dough made with pure doce flour. All doughs made with the Thai starch (the doughs from the “a” series) had more visible white clumps of starch that aggregated in the previous stage and so did not gelatinize.</p>

<p>To provide a more quantitative evaluation of how easily the different doughs deformed, we shaped them into cylinders and placed a 3.58kg mortar on top of them for 10 seconds. We then compared the height and diameters before and after weighing, removing the weight before taking our final measurements - these measurements are not in the linear deformation regime and evaluate plasticity rather than elasticity. The doughs often deformed differently across an axis due to misplacement of the mortar weight, so we took averages of the shortest and highest deformations, and always measured diameters transverse to the axis defined by shortest and highest height deformations.</p>

<p>Computing the (negative) ratio of changes in height to changes in diameter of these cylinders gives us a quantity related to the (inverse) Poisson’s ratio, a metric for the deformation (expansion / contraction) of a material perpendicular to the direction of applied stress. All of them are positive, as expected, as the cylinders expanded outwards when compressed vertically. We recorded no change in diameter for the pure azedo (sour starch) dough, whereas we did record a nonzero change in height; as this was likely due to a measurement error, we discarded this data point.</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_elasticity.png" title="pao de queijo">
          <img src="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_elasticity.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>Above we show plots generated comparing compression measurements for dough made using Thai starch and those using Brazilian sweet starch (doce) (error bars not included). The x-axis labels the percentage of the corresponding sweet starch in each dough. We had expected deformations to be of similar magnitudes when the amount of sour starch dominated over either sweet starch for both cases, and to diverge as the amount of sweet starches increased. In the end, more replicates and a more precise measurement procedure would be required to fully extract such a trend, if one exists. While dough made from Thai starch tended to flatten more along the height axis, our data measuring the increase in diameter (“diameter relaxation”) of the dough cylinders is somewhat inconclusive, with Thai and doce starches deforming more or less than each other depending on the percentage of sweet starch in the dough. At the extreme, dough made purely with Thai sweet starch tended to deform more along both vertical (height) and diametral axes than dough made with pure doce (rightmost data points of the top two plots), as we would expect from our previous observations that the Thai starch absorbs water more quickly and forms a softer dough.</p>

<p>Despite differences in the absolute axial and radial deformations of the doughs, the ratio of the plastic deformations of the doughs made purely with sweet starches converge to similar values independently of the origin of the starch (Thai or Brazilian; rightmost data point). One might expect this to mean that both doughs would behave similarly in the cooking process, though our previous notes regarding water absorption properties of the starches would suggest otherwise. In summary, our results suggest that doughs made with Thai starch are more deformable than those made from Brazilian starch, given that the former flatten around 5% more than the latter.</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_2.png" title="pao de queijo">
          <img src="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_2.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p><em>Same photo as before, but post-processing by adding eggs and cheese. All samples acquire a doughy texture, albeit the “a” series feeling smoother</em></p>

<p><em>Step 5.</em>
We shaped 4 balls of 32g each for each dough type for baking. We sprayed the oven with water to increase humidity (according to AI, this factor that should lead to thinner crusts [8]). According to our qualitative observation, sample series ib (75% Brazilian sweet starch) felt the hardest to shape.</p>

<p><em>Step 6.</em>
After baking we took measurements of the weights of all samples to evaluate water loss, cut samples in half vertically to evaluate the thickness of the crust, and took note of the crumb of the cheese breads. Our analysis indicates that, independently of the starch used, the breads lose about 15% of their weight due to baking (32 g to 28 g), with higher losses for higher concentrations of sweet starch. Breads made with Thai brand sweet tapioca starch tended to lose more water than those made with Brazilian sweet starch. This is surprising to us given the lower water content of the Asian sweet starch, but perhaps this means that the Brazilian starch has better water retention capacity. A potential explanation for this lies in the dense clumps of</p>

<figure class="half ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_water_loss.png" title="pao de queijo">
          <img src="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_water_loss.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_3.png" title="pao de queijo">
          <img src="/assets/images/pao_de_queijo_3.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>The figure above shows cross sections of our end products. Qualitative analysis of the outcomes led us to inconclusive remarks on trends, except for the sensorial observation that we should probably have included salt in the dough (which however might depend on the choice of cheese). The most noticeable effect is the flatness of the pão de queijo made by purely using Asian sweet starch (top right), which had been previously reported in Ref. [4]. Surprisingly, we unanimously felt that the recipe made purely with Brazilian sweet starch (bottom right) felt the airiest, opposite to the widespread belief that pure sour starch should lead to the lightest result [2][3]. One last, unsurprising, observation is the lack of sourness in the taste of recipes with less than 50% sour starch.</p>

<p>We estimated crust thickness using a ruler. All trials produced a crust of about 1 mm thick, set at around 15-20 minutes of cooking and resulting in a heat diffusion coefficient D ~ 0.01 mm^2/min. The dough made from 100% doce flour had the thinnest crust, we estimate around 0.5 mm, but our tools lacked the resolution to more precisely quantify these differences. Qualitatively, the crunchiness and dryness of the crusts decreased from the pure sour “s” sample (driest, crunchiest) towards doughs with more sweet starch. Pães de queijo made from at least 75% sweet starch (either variety) felt less dry and softer (i.e. easier to chew). This may indicate that the sour (azedo) starch absorbs more water than the others.</p>

<p>We baked the cheese breads in columns of four (four samples per trial) across two baking sheets, baking one tray at a time in the center rack of the oven to allow for more even heat circulation. However, since we baked multiple trials on the same pan, hot / cold spots within the oven may have contributed to some of our observations in the finished products.</p>

<p>The bottom of the pães de queijo tended to have a thicker crust than the tops. This aligned with our expectations that the surface area in more direct contact with a heating element (i.e. the heat-conducting metal pan) experienced greater heat transfer while baking and thus dried out to a greater extent than the crust exposed to the air, resulting in a thicker crust.</p>

<h2 id="conclusions-and-future-work">Conclusions and future work</h2>

<p>Here were our final verdicts on the extreme cases:</p>

<p><em>100% azedo: chewiest, hardest, flavorful but sour flavor may be too strong for some</em></p>

<p><em>100% doce: flavorless, thinnest crust, airiest</em></p>

<p><em>100% Thai starch: flat, chewy, spread out the most</em></p>

<p>Overall, we recommend using a combination of doce and azedo starches; the large air bubbles in the doce starch contribute to a light and fluffy texture while the azedo starch contributes flavor and structure. While our experience with the doce starch is somewhat at odds with other descriptions of it as contributing denseness and chewiness to the finished product, we believe our results can still be used as guidelines to help determine what combination of starches will achieve the most pleasurable texture for bakers looking to up their Brazilian cheese bread game.</p>

<p>For those interested in pushing our preliminary exploration here further, there are many avenues left to consider. Testing how moisture, fat content, and oven temperature affect the dough are natural next steps. In analogy to bread-making, higher hydration bread doughs may lead to thinner crusts and more open crumbs [11][12]. The tests we documented here could easily be attempted on blender recipes for Brazilian cheese bread [13], which naturally contain more liquid ingredients and are usually baked in a muffin pan to help set the shape of the breads. From our results above, we know that the different starches tested have different absorption properties of water. This observation is corroborated anecdotally - the best pão de queijo that one of us has had was with 100% azedo starch in a blender, resulting in a spongy bread with a slight chew, a drastically different outcome from what we observed in our experiments above with a drier dough. (this observation is strongly challenged by the purist opinion of our Brazilian author! But the whole point or our work is to determine how the recipe can be varied to please different palates and cultures)</p>

<p>We did not measure the temperature of our oven, but it is often the case that the temperature listed on the oven does not correspond to its actual temperature. Oven temperatures also tend to fluctuate considerably whenever the oven door is open, and it can take several minutes for it to subsequently get back up to temperature [14]. Oven temperatures also often require significant amounts of time to preheat to the specified temperature, even after the oven itself says it has finished preheating (this is what happens if you bake two trays of cookies in quick succession and find that the second tray bakes faster). Thus proper regulation and variation of the oven temperature using an oven-safe thermometer could provide valuable insights into how temperature affects crust thickness and texture.</p>

<p>We tasted and made observations on the crust texture of our Brazilian cheese breads within 2 hours of them being finished baking; however, a test of good pães de queijo is whether they remain moist and chewy over time. To test this, interested individuals could log observations after leaving the breads in a sealed container after baking so that humidity is retained during retrogradation, as often is the case when they are left inside heated displays in Brazilian cantinas. We expect cheese breads with thicker crusts to be drier and soften to a lesser extent than those with thinner crusts, given that more moisture from the bread interior is required to hydrate and soften a thicker crust than a thinner one.</p>

<p>Fat acts as a preservative, and the fat content in the cheese bread can also contribute to how well it holds up texturally over time. Browning of the cheese breads is intimately related to the breads’ fat and sugar content due to the Maillard reaction, so we would expect that given a fixed temperature, breads with more fat would require a shorter bake time (or alternatively, would be more easily overbaked, leading to a thicker crust). Fat can be controlled in a variety of ways here - fat / water contents of different cheeses vary, so different types of cheese may result in different textures, crumbs, and crust hardnesses; similarly, modifying the ratio of milk to water in the dough may give rise to denser or lighter final products with softer or harder crusts (given constant cooking time).</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1] <a href="https://youtu.be/kMOhrWTNGko">Alex Atala’s pão de queijo recipe</a></p>

<p>[2]  <a href=" https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gphdJnI8yag">Panelinha’s pão de queijo recipe</a></p>

<p>[3] <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskCulinary/comments/z44ecf/brazilian_cheese_bread_help/?rdt=62498">Reddit</a></p>

<p>[4] <a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/south-american-cheesy-bread-recipe">Serious Eats Brazilian cheese bread recipe</a></p>

<p>[5] Ziyu Wang, Pranita Mhaske, Asgar Farahnaky, Stefan Kasapis, Mahsa Majzoobi,
Cassava starch: Chemical modification and its impact on functional properties and digestibility, a review, Food Hydrocolloids, Volume 129, 2022, 107542, ISSN 0268-005X, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodhyd.2022.107542">DOI</a>.</p>

<p>[6] Olivier François Vilpoux, Marney Pascoli Cereda, Chapter 9 - Traditional Brazilian foods based on partial gelatinization of cassava starch: tapioca pearls (“sagu”), Brazilian tapioca (“tapioquinha”), broken tapioca pearls (“tapioca”), and popped tapioca pearls (“farinha de tapioca”), Editor(s): Marney Pascoli Cereda, Olivier François Vilpoux, Starch Industries: Processes and Innovative Products in Food and Non-Food Uses, Academic Press, 2024, Pages 211-232, ISBN 9780323908429, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-323-90842-9.00003-0">DOI</a>.</p>

<p>[7] Evaluation of the moisture content of tapioca starch using near-infrared spectroscopy. Kittisak Phetpan and Panmanas Sirisomboon. Journal of Innovative Optical Health Sciences 2015 08:02. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1142/S1793545815500145">DOI</a>.</p>

<p>[8] <a href="https://modernistcuisine.com/mbah/the-science-behind-each-stage-of-the-bread-making-process/#:~:text=This%20process%20is%20called%20gelatinization,molecules%20form%20a%20set%20gel">Nathan Myrvhold’s blog (Modernist Cuisine).</a></p>

<p>[9] <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/food-science/starch-gelatinization">Gelatinization overview</a></p>

<p>[10] <a href="https://brasilagosto.org/en/manioc-starch/">Tapioca starch processing.</a></p>

<p>[11] <a href="https://www.kingarthurbaking.com/blog/2021/08/16/with-bread-is-wetter-better-high-hydration-dough">King Arthur Flour article on dough hydration.</a></p>

<p>[12] <a href="https://beginwithbutter.com/baking-science-dough-hydration/">Baking Science article on dough hydration.</a></p>

<p>[13] <a href="https://www.oliviascuisine.com/easy-pao-de-queijo/">Blender pão de queijo recipe.</a></p>

<p>[14] <a href="https://www.thekitchn.com/quick-tip-keep-the-oven-door-c-77104#">The Kitchn article on oven temperatures.</a></p>

<p>[15] <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starch">Wikipedia page on starch.</a></p>

<p>[16] <a href="https://bakerpedia.com/processes/starch-gelatinization/">Bakerpedia.</a></p>

<p>[17] <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/6741f94e-a62c-8010-948b-3acb5b85e9b6">Chat GPT.</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Through fall season, Harvard hosts a Science &amp; Cooking course, where science topics relevant for cooking such as soft matter, organic chemistry, heat transport, and diffusion, are discussed. This course is often accompanied by a series of public lectures working as an outreach activity to engage the lay community.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Charter your scientific team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/12/group_charter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Charter your scientific team" /><published>2024-11-12T08:05:54-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T08:05:54-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/12/group_charter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/12/group_charter.html"><![CDATA[<p>Basic project management often begins with a charter—a set of agreements that define the rules and expectations for team collaboration. I believe a team charter can be just as valuable for a scientific group, whether newly formed or well-established.</p>

<p>A group charter helps teams avoid conflicts and offers a framework for resolving them when they arise. These guidelines can set expectations around attendance, meeting etiquette (e.g., lateness, device use), and more. Below is a non-exhaustive list of team charter items and questions that might be relevant for scientific and other types of groups:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What is the acceptable tardiness for meetings? does prior notice matter?</li>
  <li>How much work-from-home is acceptable? What are the policies and limits?</li>
  <li>Is calendar blocking for uninterrupted work acceptable? By how much?</li>
  <li>Expected response times for emails and direct messages; how to classify urgency.</li>
  <li>How authorship for publications is defined?</li>
  <li>What allotted time acceptable to spend on skill-building, learning, and conferences?</li>
  <li>Note-taking responsibilities; is it important for the team, and should the duty rotate?</li>
  <li>Frequency and length of meetings with team leaders.</li>
</ul>

<p>Charters can also reflect a team’s core values, which can enhance hiring by helping candidates assess if they are a cultural fit. Likewise, they help hiring managers gauge how well candidates’ backgrounds and mindsets align with team values. These uses serve both for the purposes of evaluating general team-candidate alignment, but also for identifying complementary misalignments that can actually benefit all. Here is a set of core values I have been developing which can serve as an example or inspiration:</p>

<h5 id="1-passion-for-creation">1. Passion for Creation</h5>
<p>Science and engineering flow from the practitioner into the world, via their hands, voice and gestures. They express themselves through production outcomes, which may take the form of arguments, calculations, devices, simulations, and the like. Our group prioritizes a genuine drive for creative output, free of ego, and striving for daily contributions which are celebrated independently of being small or large. We also target the experimental plausibility or realization of ideas as the ultimate goal of all creation effort.</p>

<h5 id="2-quality-by-cultivation">2. Quality by cultivation</h5>
<p>The creative, socioeconomic, or cultural value of the engineer or scientist output is limited by the individual’s breadth and depth of knowledge. We cultivate solid learning practices and a relentless learning spirit, letting information flow from the world into us via our vision, hearing, attention, touch, and smell. We reject using jargon to hide misunderstandings, and strive for knowledge and understanding standards that ensure high quality for all we create.</p>

<h5 id="3-sustainability-as-the-scaffold">3. Sustainability as the scaffold</h5>
<p>Sustained creation and learning requires a healthy body, grit, a diversity of perspectives, and a respectful environment. We welcome all backgrounds and prioritize well-being and community, fostering connections within the team and beyond. This respect for sustainable practice reflects the accountability we have to society as scientists and engineers.</p>

<hr />
<p>I’d like to acknowledge that this is not the first version of core values for scientific groups I ever thought about, and probably won’t be the last. Feedback and comments are welcome on LinkedIn, as always.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Basic project management often begins with a charter—a set of agreements that define the rules and expectations for team collaboration. I believe a team charter can be just as valuable for a scientific group, whether newly formed or well-established.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Effective team training and who should lead it?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/students_teaching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effective team training and who should lead it?" /><published>2024-10-20T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/students_teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/students_teaching.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lazy blogging. I don’t want to reblog a topic someone else just did. So I will just point people to this interesting piece on <a href="https://condensedconcepts.blogspot.com/2024/06/should-phd-students-choose-to-teach.html">should students teach?</a> at Condensed Concepts. I think the only perspective I should add is that even in private industry, training is extremely important. Onboarding new team members always takes times, does not matter how well-prepared they are. Experience in doing it effectively can be helpful. Understanding the value of it can help save time and money to your organization. Particularly for managers: if you want things done a given way, common recommendation is to train your direct reports on how that is.</p>

<p>Even more importantly, do not forget to tell them “why” you want things that way. It will help people not going out of line, or help you get them back in place when they do. Find more lessons on this in <a href="https://a16z.com/books/the-hard-thing-about-hard-things/">“The Hard Thing About Hard Things”</a> by A16Z.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lazy blogging. I don’t want to reblog a topic someone else just did. So I will just point people to this interesting piece on should students teach? at Condensed Concepts. I think the only perspective I should add is that even in private industry, training is extremely important. Onboarding new team members always takes times, does not matter how well-prepared they are. Experience in doing it effectively can be helpful. Understanding the value of it can help save time and money to your organization. Particularly for managers: if you want things done a given way, common recommendation is to train your direct reports on how that is.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Drive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/14/Drive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drive" /><published>2024-09-14T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-14T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/14/Drive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/14/Drive.html"><![CDATA[<p>In my journey to expand my knowledge from physics to effective management practices, I maintain a steady, yet unhurried reading pace. I find the experience enjoyable—much more engaging than some of my fellow scientists might expect. Many books in this field offer fresh, modern insights, often grounded in solid science. In this post, I’ll give a quick review of a recent favorite: “<a href="https://www.thriftbooks.com/w/drive-the-surprising-truth-about-what-motivates-us_daniel-h-pink/246588/?resultid=f8f87171-a9f2-404a-9610-3ab7705fcda7#edition=5980628&amp;idiq=3847557">Drive</a>”, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_H._Pink">Daniel H. Pink</a>.</p>

<p>Amusingly, the author makes my job easy: at the end of the book, he includes “social media” and “cocktail party” summaries. I’ll draw on some of those but also add my own insights.</p>

<p>The book’s main takeaway is that our traditional understanding of motivation—particularly for workers, employees, and even ourselves—is outdated. Not only is this “common wisdom” ineffective for modern needs, but it can also be harmful. What is this outdated wisdom? The author refers to it as the “carrots &amp; sticks” approach: rewarding positive behaviors or achievements and punishing shortcomings.</p>

<p>However, scientific research in psychology, economics, and management suggests a better path. The author argues for a new model of motivation based on three elements:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Autonomy</em> – The desire and ability to direct one’s own life.</li>
  <li><em>Mastery</em> – The drive to improve at something that matters.</li>
  <li><em>Purpose</em> – The sense that what we do is bigger than ourselves and serves others.</li>
</ul>

<p>I find that I can logically relate to many of the arguments put forward by the book supporting the structure above. For example, it suggests that repetitive tasks don’t necessarily have to harm motivation. A basketball player might shoot thousands of hoops to develop <em>mastery</em>, just as I’ve computed an unexciting number of derivatives to get good at calculus. What lies behind this behavior is the idea that humans are capable of intrinsic motivation. While “carrots &amp; sticks” are clear and easy-to-understand extrinsic motivators, they can undermine this intrinsic drive, which is often more powerful, especially for jobs that involve creativity or critical thinking.</p>

<p>D. Pink fills the book with examples showing how these “if-then” extrinsic motivators can harm motivation—crushing creativity, lowering performance, and even discouraging positive behavior. To his credit, the author also acknowledges cases where extrinsic motivation can be beneficial, offering insights into how to align it with the three elements of autonomy, mastery, and purpose. One practical proposition is to shift from “if-then” to “now-that” rewards: offering unexpected rewards only after a task is completed, which can boost motivation without overshadowing intrinsic drive.</p>

<p>Perhaps my favorite idea in the book is that while extrinsic effects don’t usually work for improving motivation, the lack of a reasonable baseline of extrinsic incentives can be highly damaging. As the book points out, things like salaries and benefits need to be taken out of the equation as soon as possible. Workers should receive competitive pay and benefits to create a basic sense of fairness and stability for themselves and their loved ones. Beyond that point, large bonuses or harsh penalties won’t boost productivity or efficiency. That’s when the focus should shift to the three key elements: autonomy, mastery, and purpose. I can definitely see this position mattering in scientific environments.</p>

<p>A key strength of the book is that its arguments aren’t just the author’s opinions—they’re grounded in scientific research by behavioral scientists like (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_L._Deci">Edward Deci</a>) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaly_Csikszentmihalyi">Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi</a>, provided we should appreciate some of these figures may be a bit controversial. I also find that the book’s insights into the role of Purpose in motivation echo themes explored by philosophers, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byung-Chul_Han">Byung-chul Han</a> in his work, “<a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262533379/the-agony-of-eros/">Agony of Eros</a>”.</p>

<p>As with any complex topic, there’s no one-size-fits-all solution to the problem of motivation (particularly in a scientific environment). Still, I find this book thoughtful and full of valuable insights—whether for organizations facing challenges or those looking to elevate their practices.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my journey to expand my knowledge from physics to effective management practices, I maintain a steady, yet unhurried reading pace. I find the experience enjoyable—much more engaging than some of my fellow scientists might expect. Many books in this field offer fresh, modern insights, often grounded in solid science. In this post, I’ll give a quick review of a recent favorite: “Drive”, by Daniel H. Pink.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cash Flower</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/12/cash_flower.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cash Flower" /><published>2024-08-12T09:05:54-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-12T09:05:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/08/12/cash_flower</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/12/cash_flower.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I have written posts on the challenges and subtleties of keeping a healthy funding stream for a scientific team. We have also covered some creative practices and opportunities to mitigate some of the risks involved and challenges identified.</p>

<p>This is my own attempt at contributing something to this cause. Keeping track of a group’s finances can be tricky; being able to forecast one’s funding capacity, measuring opportunities against burning rates, can be the difference between being caught unprepared or stably honoring the trust other researchers put on the team manager. Thus, I introduce the “Cash Flower”, a simple Monte Carlo program to provide financial forecasts for an organization funded by typical means a researcher may encounter. Find the source and installation insructions on <a href="https://github.com/pedrolslopes/Cash_Flower">this repo</a>.</p>

<p>Financial data can be input in four different types of categories:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Stable</strong>: Constant sources of income or expense (e.g., salaries, bills, IP licenses), characterized by monthly average values and variances.</li>
  <li><strong>Singles</strong>: One-time revenue or expense events (e.g., rare large sales, purchases).</li>
  <li><strong>Recurrent</strong>: Repeated cash flows triggered after an initial event (e.g., long-term deals, scholarships, sales or purchase of established products).</li>
  <li><strong>Project</strong>: Milestone-based cash flows tied to project success and timing (e.g. grants).</li>
</ul>

<p>Users may flexibly encode data from their different funding streams in the categories above, with pre-determined probabilities of realizing each event, according to preferences, convenience, or mindset. No single right way of doing it.</p>

<p>Given a set of financial data, Cash Flower outputs some traditional data analytics upon estimating several scenarios of success or failure at achieving revenue or expenses. These analytics include, for the moment, monthly revenue/expense reports, an analysis of the accumulated funding in the organization as function of time, and the risk of going negative. Here goes what the generated plots can look like for some example data:</p>

<figure class=" ">
  
    
      <a href="/assets/images/cash_flower_analysis_example.png" title="Cash Flower Data Analysis">
          <img src="/assets/images/cash_flower_analysis_example.png" alt="graph" />
      </a>
    
  
  
</figure>

<p>This program is open source and all are welcome to contribute to the project. Some of my current ideas for improvement include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Better visuals for histogram of monthly expenses and gains.</li>
  <li>Change data gathering and reading scheme so users can take resources from Excel spreadsheets or Pandas dataframes.</li>
  <li>Plot categorized data according to the different types of cashflow events, evaluating how important each is at a given time.</li>
</ul>

<p>Bug reports are also welcome, particularly identifying situations where the program fails!</p>

<p>I hope Cash Flower will help scientific managers and individual contributors alike to better monitor the financial health of their endeavours!</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: as of the writing of this post, these resources have not yet been tested on realistic scenarios.</em></p>

<p><em>For this one I owe a big thanks to my wife, Marianne, for the support, helping with debugging, and feature suggestions. Hope this will be useful to her one day! I also owe the idea for creating this program to Yuval Boger, “The Superposition Guy”.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Pedro LS Lopes</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently I have written posts on the challenges and subtleties of keeping a healthy funding stream for a scientific team. We have also covered some creative practices and opportunities to mitigate some of the risks involved and challenges identified.]]></summary></entry></feed>